<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The touch-stone of prayer. Or A true and profitable exposition of the Lords prayer, according to the holy Hebrew of S. Mathews gospel to which is prefixed certaine necessary circumstances to be obserued in prayer. Also thereunto is annexed a table shewing the agreement betweene the Lords prayer, and the ten commandements of Almighty God. By T.S.</title>
            <author>S., Tho.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11258</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21523</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114099</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849327</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849327</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14467</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11258)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14467)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1494:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The touch-stone of prayer. Or A true and profitable exposition of the Lords prayer, according to the holy Hebrew of S. Mathews gospel to which is prefixed certaine necessary circumstances to be obserued in prayer. Also thereunto is annexed a table shewing the agreement betweene the Lords prayer, and the ten commandements of Almighty God. By T.S.</title>
                  <author>S., Tho.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[128] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For Arthur Iohnson, dwelling in Paules church-yarde, at the signe of the Flower de Luce and Crowne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14467:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14467:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE TOVCH-STONE of Prayer.</p>
            <p>Or A true and profitable expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Lords Prayer, according to the holy Hebrew of <hi>S. Mathews</hi> goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel: to which is prefixed certaine neceſſary circumſtances to be obſerued in Prayer.</p>
            <p>Alſo thereunto is annexed a Table ſhewing the agreement betweene the Lords prayer, and the ten comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of Almighty God.</p>
            <p>By T. S.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Whatſoeuer yee ſhall aske, if yee beleeue, yee ſhall receiue it.</hi> 
               <bibl>Mat. 21. 22.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q xml:lang="lat">Oratio pia penetrat coelum.</q>
            <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>Arthur Iohnſon,</hi> dwelling in Paules Church-yarde, at the ſigne of the Flower de Luce and Crowne. 1602.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14467:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14467:2"/>
            <head>To the religious gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <hi>Maiſter</hi> Robert Bate, <hi>and Maiſter</hi> Edmund Sleigh: T. S. <hi>wiſheth in this life the feare of God, and in the life to come euerlaſting rest with Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing compiled this little Treatiſe, at the motion of a priuate friend, moſt eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie for his benefit and mine owne comfort, once an entrance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made into the matter: I found ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie good and profitable leſſons, naturally to ariſe from this ſo excellent a ſubiect, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a moſt abſolute forme of prayer, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered by the bleſſed mouth of Chriſt our Sauiour, vnto his diſciples, at his inſtant requeſt, I thought it could not, but be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie profitable to others, as I finding the meditation hereof ſo ſweete vnto my
<pb facs="tcp:14467:3"/> ſelfe. Now this ſerious cogitation was a ſtrong motiue vnto me, to publiſh that abroad, which I thought to keepe priuate to my ſelfe and to my friend; who firſt mooued me to take in hand this taske, to which ſo much the rather I condiſcended: being inſtantly vrged therevnto, by ſome of my very friends, to whom I imparted the ſight of this ſmall worke: affirming that our knowledge ſhould not be inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed within the narrowe bounds of our owne breſt, but to be extended, as much as is poſſible, to the benefit of others. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though many vigilant watchmen ouer Chriſtes flocke, and induſtrious labourers in his great harueſt: haue taken great paines in the vnfoulding the miſteries of this moſt perfect platforme of prayer, without doubt to the benefit of the church) yet I know, it is not a thing ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous (as it may ſeeme to ſome) but moſt neceſſarie in theſe times, to refreſh the memorie of their learned labours. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though praier be a daily exerciſe amongſt vs, yet the number is very ſmall that know
<pb facs="tcp:14467:3"/> to performe this holy action with true ſincerity. So that indeedo, that which ſhould be a ſhield vnto them to defend from the aſſaults of our olde enemie: is a iuſt cauſe to make the Lord to vnſneath his two-edged ſword againſt them. Some are ſo nouſled in ſecuritie, that they offer vp the calues of their lippes, as <hi>Caine</hi> did his ſacrifice, that is by hands of others, and thinke all is well, if they giue a conſent with their voice to a generall prayer, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God knoweth, their hearts are wandring abroad at that inſtant; others haue a zeale, but it is without vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo that they know not how to pray aright, nor to whom to pray as they ought; but like the <hi>Athenians,</hi> worſhip an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne God, and others are ſo beſotted with a blinde deuotion, that they thinke their prayers cannot be ſanctified, vnleſſe they be holyed with Popiſh reliques. All theſe things with many more duly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, it is as cleare as the light, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth euery true Chriſtian, (ſo farre as it ſhall pleaſe God to enhable him) to labor
<pb facs="tcp:14467:4"/> to remoue theſe impediments. And albeit I humbly acknowledge my ſelfe to be one of the meaneſt among my bretheren to vndergoe this labour, yet ſeeing it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Lord, by weake meanes, to bring mighty things to paſſe, whereby his glory ſhineth the brighter. I was not diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to employ my ſmall talent, which it hath pleaſed him to beſtow on me, to the benefit of others, (I hope,) aſwell as of my ſelfe. And as I wiſh it may be to the glory of God, and the vniuerſall good of all, ſo more perticulerly, to the comfort of you my very good friends and louing countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whome I haue choſen, as patrons of my ſmall worke, aſwell to teſtifie my gratefull minde towardes you, as that by your protection it might the better be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, from the malicious tongues of ſuch as ſhall carpe againſt it: being fully reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of your fauourable acceptance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I know you are religious obſeruers of this diuine exerciſe, and well inſtructed in the word of God, which is our true Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot to direct our courſe aright. In the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb facs="tcp:14467:4"/> of this ſhort, but moſt abſolute and ſweete prayer, of which our Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus, is the author, and therefore is vſually named the Lords prayer: I haue followed the Hebrew text, eſpecially for three reſpects. Firſt, becauſe it is the natiue tongue of the Goſpell, wherein this pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was firſt penned: ſecondly, becauſe more neceſſarie, more ſignificant, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly leſſons are naturally to be learned from the holy Hebrew words, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered by themſelues, then from any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther language. Thirdly, I was inſtigated to take this courſe by the examples of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers famous and learned doctors, namely that learned and reuerend Doctor <hi>Saint Ierome,</hi> deuine <hi>Theophilact, Simon Grineus,</hi> and <hi>Sebaſtian Munſter,</hi> and many others, both old and new writers, who follow the Hebrew text of this Goſpell, and may be vnto me as ſtrong defenſiue Bulwarkes, againſt ſuch as might happily impeach this maner of proceeding. But if it ſhall pleaſe God to reueale to any other a more expedite courſe, let him in Gods name,
<pb facs="tcp:14467:5"/> with a good conſcience vſe his owne li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie; It ſhall ſuffice me amongſt the reſt to bring ſomewhat to the building of the Lords ſpirituall Temple, be it neuer ſo meane, ſo it doe ſerue for the edification thereof. But to auoide tediouſneſſe, fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leaſt I haue offended already in this reſpect, I commit you and all the reſt of my louing friends and Country-men to the protection of the omnipotent, and onely wiſe God, and my labours whatſoeuer, to his good bleſſing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Country-man moſt humbly to commaund <hi>T. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14467:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the godly and</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as much (gentle Reader) as nothing is more neceſsary and profitable to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, yea more plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing to God: then is the faithfull prayers of his elect. And becauſe all in the church, haue not like meaſure of knowledge: to know eyther for what: or after what manner to pray, I haue thought it good for the benefit of ſuch weake ones, to ſet forth this expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lordes prayer: which is the abſolute for me of all holy prayers, the doctrines I haue drawne from the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall meaning of the wordes, as they are ſet downe in the holy Hebrew of S. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewes</hi> goſpell, vſing no curioſitie in method: but handling euery word as it lyeth in order in the text, which is the
<pb facs="tcp:14467:6"/> plaineſt, and eaſieſt, for the capacity of the ſimpler ſort, that can be: And for their better vnderſtanding how to pray, I haue prefixed certaine circumſtances of prayer, which are ſeriouſly to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of euery one that will pray aright. Laſtly to the end of the Lordes prayer, I haue added a table, ſhewing thee the agreement of the Lordes prayer with the ten commaundementes. And whereas in reading, thou ſhalt ſee this marke *. At the beginning of any ſentence, looke on the margent, and it ſheweth thee the writer, from whence that ſentence was borrowed: and becauſe that ſome may thinke my enterpriſe bould, yea and this my doing to be altogether needeleſſe, in as much as I haue but buſied my ſelfe, with that which my betters haue both learnedly taught, and writ: the which notwithſtanding, we ſtill continuing in our ſecurity, and careleſneſſe, thinking in
<pb facs="tcp:14467:6"/> our proſperity, we ſhall neuer be caſt downe: putting farre from vs the euill day, which amongſt many, is the moſt deſperate diſeaſe to the ſoule, that can be. Alſo conſidering with my ſelfe, the duty I owe to God, remembring, how euery one muſt giue an account how he hath vſed his talent: yea religion bindeth me to haue a louing care of the ſaluation of my brethren, and the duty and loue I beare to the church, wherein I liue, and of which I am a member: theſe and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more ſuch like reaſons, cauſe me to ſay, the loue of God in Chriſt Ieſus conſtraines me to ſpeake that I doe: and with the Apoſtles in the Acts, I cannot chuſe but ſpeake the things I haue heard and ſeene. Neyther gentle reader, let this worke ſeeme to thee ſuperfluous, becauſe ſome learned haue entreated of the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before, we ſee by lamentable expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience how ſoone their learned labours
<pb facs="tcp:14467:7"/> are forgot, and how ſeldome put in prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, therefore we cannot heare a good thing too often, nor learne it too well. And I beſeech God for his ſonnes ſake to take the ſcales from our eyes, that our affections may be illuminated, and we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrengthened in the inner man: may the better diſcharge ſo waighty a duty as praier is. Read this booke, (chriſtian bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) with a ſingle eye, not onely ſo much to know, as to practiſe: and to be penitent for that which hath beene amiſſe: and that humility, and meeknes, dwelling in thy ſoule, God may guide thy iudgement, and teach thee in his way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that thou <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25</note> vſe this booke, no otherwiſe then it was meant, to thy good and comfort, which God grant vnto thee, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy louing brother in Chriſt Ieſus</hi> Tho. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:7"/>
               <l>QViſquis amas Christum, ſanctè componere vota,</l>
               <l>Diſcas, Diabolum ſic ſuperare potes.</l>
               <l>Ipſe licet nobis minitetur vulnera Daemon,</l>
               <l>Saepe precare Deum, vulnera nulla feres.</l>
               <l>Contrà nos tumidae minitantur praelia Gentes</l>
               <l>Exitiumque parant, Perdere nemo poteſt.</l>
               <l>Nam Dius, exaudit iuſtorum tempore duro</l>
               <l>Cum clamant, gemitus, auxilium que feret.</l>
               <l>Corda leuate Deo, mundanas ſpernite curas,</l>
               <l>Impediunt votum, pondere corda premunt,</l>
               <l>Sanctificet que fides ſemper pia dicta precantis,</l>
               <l>Haec mentem ſanctam redere ſola ſolet.</l>
               <l>Hac iter ad vitam, hac magnitecta Tonantis</l>
               <l>Scandimus eloqvio, Pax vbi ſola manet.</l>
               <l>Sintque manus purae nobis, ſint pectora pura,</l>
               <l>Sic Dominus precibus cuncta petita dabit.</l>
               <l>Chriſtus diſcipulos docuit pia verba referre,</l>
               <l>Hoc docet exemplo, nos quo que verba pia.</l>
               <l>Quis poterit Chriſti magnae praeconia laudis</l>
               <l>Dicere pro meritis? dicere nemo queat.</l>
               <l>Qui monſtrare viam voluit, qua culmina coeli</l>
               <l>Scandimus, atque patri ſacra referre ſuo.</l>
               <l>Non pudeat ſanctos ſanctam didiciſſe loquelam,</l>
               <l>Omnia nam ſanctis obuia ſunt precibus</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t docuiſti tuos olim mitiſſime Chriſte</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:8"/>
               <l> Diſcipulos, verbo nos quoque paſce tuo.</l>
               <l>Tempora, concedas vitae faelicia nobis,</l>
               <l>Sit tibi, ſitque patri gloria lauſque tuo.</l>
            </lg>
            <q>Oratio abſque fide, eſt quaſi corpus ſine anima.</q>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraphs">
            <p>
               <hi>To the ſecure and careleſſe ſaith</hi> S. Iames.</p>
            <q>Yee luſt and haue not: becauſe yee aske not. <bibl>
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 4. <hi>verſe.</hi> 2.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>To the laſciuious and carnall.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Yee aske and receiue not: becauſe yee aske amiſſe. <bibl>
                  <hi>verſe</hi> 3.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>To the regenerate Chriſtian ſaith</hi> S. Iohn.</p>
            <q>This is the aſſurance that we haue in him, that if we aske any thing according to his will, he hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs. <bibl>
                  <hi>John.</hi> 5. <hi>verſe</hi> 14. 15.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Before we crie will hee anſwere: and whilſt wee ſpeake will he heare vs. <bibl>
                  <hi>Jſa.</hi> 65. <hi>verſ.</hi> 24.</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="observations">
            <pb facs="tcp:14467:8"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Obſeruations to <hi>praie aright.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>Eight leſſons, or neceſſary obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to be learned of all, that will pray aright.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S no exerciſes can be wel performed, without ſome cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rylie thereto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing: whether we reſpect exerciſes of the body, or of the minde. So prayer being an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe ordained of God: then the which nothing is more profitable, can in no good meaſure on our part be performed: without ſome ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary circumſtances thereto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing. The conſideration where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb facs="tcp:14467:9"/> hath cauſed me, to place before the Lordes prayer, theſe eight ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary circumſtances, belonging to <note place="margin">To whom we muſt pray.</note> prayer. The firſt whereof is, to whom we muſt pray.</p>
            <p>For as it is ridiculous to vtter <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Circū∣ſtance. </seg>1</label> much ſpeach vnto them, who are neither carefull, nor capable of that we ſay: and as it is great ſimplicity, for any to deliuer a ſupplication vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the cooke, which perteineth to the king, ſo much more folly is it, for any to pray vnto Angell or Saint, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Papiſts in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like the</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> ſeeing we may iuſtly doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they heare, or can giue vs what we want. And if any ſo doe, he is as blinde as the <hi>Athenians,</hi> to pray to an vnknowne God. Therefore we muſt pray to him, that is willing to helpe vs, which alſo is incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible in all places to heare vs, and alſufficient able to giue vs, els can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:14467:9"/> our prayers be made in faith. And if they be not in faith, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, whatſoeuer is not of faith is ſinne. But prayer to Saints cannot be of faith: therefore ſuch prayers are ſinne: Againe we can pray to none, but to them we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in. But we muſt beleeue onely in God: Therefore pray to him one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>Our ſauiours wordes, which ought to be without contradiction, teach vs that plainely.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and him onely ſhalt thou ſerue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that this is a part of Gods worſhip, and honour to be prayed vnto: heare what the Prophet ſaith in the perſon of God. <hi>Call vpon me</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 50.</note> 
               <hi>and I will deliuer thee, and thou ſhall glorifie me:</hi> and looke into the verſe before, and thou ſhalt finde: he that
<pb facs="tcp:14467:10"/> giues this commandement, is the moſt high and bleſſed Trinity.</p>
            <div n="2" type="observation">
               <head>The ſecond Circumſtance.</head>
               <p>THe ſecond obſeruation is, to <note place="margin">We muſt pray in the name of Chriſt.</note> know through whom, or in whoſe name, to offer vp our praiers: and that is, in Chriſtes name: ſo doth <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. 3.</note> the Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> teache vs. <hi>There is one God, and one mediator: betweene God and man, the man Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>if any</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>man ſinne, we haue an aduocate with the father, Ieſus Chriſt the righteous.</hi> And Chriſt him ſelfe hath witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, whatſoeuer we ſhall aske the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> in his name, we ſhall receiue it. Therefore ſath the bleſſed Apoſtle, we haue boldnes, and entrance, with confidence, through faith in him, that is in Chriſt, and not in any An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell or Saint.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="observation">
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:10"/>
               <head>The third circumſtance.</head>
               <p>IN the third place, obſerue for what <note place="margin">
                     <hi>For what to pray.</hi> Mat. 6</note> to pray, of this doth Chriſt teach vs, in <hi>Mathew</hi> the ſixt. Euen in the Lordes prayer, which is a true pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne for all holy prayers: whereof ſhall be ſpoken more at large in his place, In the meane time obſerue this leſſon of S. <hi>Paule.</hi> I exhort (ſaith <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. 1.</note> he) that prayers, and ſupplications, and interceſſions, and giuing of <note place="margin">Why we must pray for Kings.</note> thankes be made for all men: for kings, and all that be in authority; that we may leade a quiet &amp; peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able life, in all godlineſſe and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty for this is good, and acceptable in the ſight of God our Sauiour. Wherefore with <hi>Theophilact</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude <note place="margin">Theo: on Luke cha. 11.</note> this point: that he which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that which is not profitable for the ſoule, nor neceſſary for the body,
<pb facs="tcp:14467:11"/> ſhall not be hard. For ſaith that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father with God, ſuch are no pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, if they aske, <hi>Quae non expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt,</hi> ſuch things, as are neither ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary nor fit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="observation">
               <head>The fourth Circumſtance.</head>
               <p>THe fourth point to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is the cauſes that mooue vs to prayer, and amongſt many I will only name foure.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe God hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it. <hi>Call vpon me, ſaith</hi> IEHOVAH. <note place="margin">Pſal. 50</note> 
                  <hi>Aske, ſaith</hi> CHRIST.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the promiſe of God: <note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>And I will deliuer thee, and yee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it.</hi> Here is the promiſe of God, therefore ſaid a writer well. <hi>I Deus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gulia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus on Mat. 6. pa. 132.</note> 
                  <hi>ſimul iuſsit or are, et promiſit exaudire.</hi> God at once commanded to pray, and he hath promiſed to heare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly or louingly.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:11"/>
               <p> Thirdly, the feeling of our owne <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Mo∣tiue to Prayer. </seg>3</label> miſeries: By the example of <hi>Dauid</hi> of <hi>Iob,</hi> of <hi>Ionah,</hi> alſo the Hebrew word ſet downe by Saint <hi>Mathew.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 4. 2 Iob. 6.</note> VEATTEM KEN TITHPALLELV. <hi>Yee ſhall pray thus,</hi> the roote of which <note place="margin">Ionah. 2 Mat. 6.</note> worde is PALAL, which in the firſt ſence, or to ſpeake according to the Grammer, it is in the firſt, or light coniugation, <hi>to iudge,</hi> and as here it is, in the fourth coniugation, called with Grammarians HITHPALL, it ſignifieth, <hi>to iudge a mans ſelfe,</hi> for <hi>actio eiuſdem in ſeipſum,</hi> is an action of the ſame man vpon himſelfe; ſo it ſignifieth here in this place, as if he ſhould haue ſaid, <note n="*" place="margin">For our Sauiour hath left vs a prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may iudge our ſelues, our prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and all our actions.</note> 
                  <hi>And yee ſhall iudge your ſelues thus,</hi> &amp;c. For indeed, no man can pray aright, except he firſt iudge himſelfe: and if he do ſo, the Apoſtle telleth him he ſhall not be iudged of the Lord. And here
<pb facs="tcp:14467:12"/> we may conſider, the very ende of prayer, <hi>vt obediamus Deo et impetre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gulia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus on Mat. 6. pa. 132.</note> 
                  <hi>à deo:</hi> euen that we may obey God, &amp; obtaine by our requeſts fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, <note n="*" place="margin">4. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to prayer.</hi>
                  </note> &amp; this may wel be conſidered in the laſt motiue to praier: which is the benefits we receiue by prayer. The benefits are exceeding great, and he moſt faithfull which hath promiſed the ſame, which is Chriſt; whatſoeuer you ſhall aske the father <note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> in my name, ye ſhall receiue it (ſaith <note place="margin">Mar. 9.</note> our Sauiour) what neede I to recite <note place="margin">Mat. 15 28.</note> here, how all the godly haue beene deliuered by prayer, in their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt dangers: how fathers haue had their ſonnes healed, the mothers their daughters, Yea <hi>Cornelius</hi> had <hi>Peter</hi> to cure his ſoule, a iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe is this his example to all ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and lukewarme Chriſtians, for he delighted in prayer, before his <note place="margin">Acts. 10</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:12"/> conuerſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> by prayer receiued a ſonne: an † <hi>Iſaack</hi> a ſonne <hi>of laughter,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Of שחק to laugh.</note> for God turned his mourning into ioy. For he meaned becauſe he was childeleſſe as appeareth. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anna</hi> prayed and had not onely a Sonne, but euen a Prophet of the higheſt: for ſhe begged him of God and therefore ſhee called his name <note n="*a" place="margin">Of שאל to aske. 1. Sam. 1. 20. § Luk. 1</note> 
                  <hi>Shemuel</hi> § alſo <hi>Zachary</hi> by his prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers obtained a ſonne in his old age, for by his prayers he found grace with God. Therefore he called his name <note n="*" place="margin">Of חנן to ſhew mercy.</note> 
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> To conclude there is no ende of Gods mercy to a man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed with prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="observation">
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:13"/>
               <head>The fift Circumſtance.</head>
               <p>THe fift leſſon to be obſerued is the place where to pray, the <note place="margin">The place where.</note> 
                  <hi>Predicament vbi,</hi> as <hi>Logicians</hi> call it, maketh much for the praiſe or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe of any thing, &amp; therefore the Phariſies loued to ſtand in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket place and pray. But Chriſtians <note place="margin">Ma. 6. 5</note> haue another leſſon, for Chriſtbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thee, enter into thy ſecret cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, (not but that it is lawfull to pray any where.) For ſaith Chriſt to the <note place="margin">Ioh. 4. 21. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Samaritane</hi> woman. The true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers, ſhall neither worſhip in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> nor in this mount: but in ſpirit and trueth, and the Apoſtle <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith, pray euery where, lifting vp pure handes with out wrath or doubting. For publique prayers, we haue Chriſtes promiſe: when two or three are gathered togeather <note place="margin">Mat. 18</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:13"/> in my name, there am I in the midſt of them; and from this an ancient father ſaith very well, <hi>et propterea</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Theo.</note> 
                  <hi>ſaepe precantes non accipimus, eo quod mutua concordia caremus.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore often times praying, we receiue not, becauſe we haue not brotherly fellowſhip: for where there is loue, conſolation, piety, and religion: there Chriſt doth not ſay, I will be, but Iam in the midſt of them: but for our priuate prayers, Chriſt tolde vs, our ſecret chamber was the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, and he confirmed it vnto vs, by his owne examples: as when he ſaid to his diſciples, ſit you here, whilſt I <note place="margin">Mat. 26</note> go and pray yonder. Alſo whereas he went vp in to the Mountaine to pray: from whence that reuerend Archſhop <hi>Theophilact,</hi> noteth thus much, <hi>oportet nos ſolitarioseſſe, et nullis rebus terrenis intendere orando:</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooueth
<pb facs="tcp:14467:14"/> vs to be ſolitarie, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our mindes to no earthly mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whilſt we are in praying.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="observation">
               <head>The ſixt Obſeruation from the predic a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of time, when and how long to pray.</head>
               <p>OVr ſauiour ſaith it muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Circū∣ſtance. </seg>6</label> this continuance in prayer, will liuely ſet forth our faith and conſtancie in God: to wraſtle with God as <hi>Iacob</hi> did, till wee haue <note place="margin">Hoſ. 3</note> a bleſſing, which muſt be obtained by the ſame manner, that this was, by weeping &amp; praying, neither with <note place="margin">Luk. 18</note> the widow muſt we giue ouer, till our cauſe be heard; <hi>Anna</hi> continued <note place="margin">Luk. 1</note> in prayers night and day. And <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi> three times a day. How oft hath <note place="margin">Dan. 5</note> Chriſt prayed all night? and was it not for our ſakes miſerable ſinners.
<pb facs="tcp:14467:14"/> Therefore let vs watch one houre <note place="margin">Mat. 26</note> and not ſleepe as <hi>Peter</hi> did, leaſt we fall into temptation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="observation">
               <head>Seauenthly with what affections we muſt pray.</head>
               <p>WIth zeale and feruencie, ſo <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Circū∣ſtance. </seg>7</label> ſaith <hi>Paule,</hi> be feruent in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Iames, the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ro. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>of a righteous man auayleth much if it be feruent.</hi> With the Publican wee <note place="margin">Iam. 5</note> muſt knock our breſt, and with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> ſay Lord enter not into Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Pſalm. 133. 2.</note> with thy ſeruant. With <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> pray vehemently, to cry with <note place="margin">Ier. 14. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieremy</hi> our iniquities teſtifie againſt vs: with <hi>Daniel, O Lord heare, O Lord</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>helpe, O Lord conſider:</hi> and howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer our affections are maruelouſly dulled, by reaſon of the fraileneſſe <note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> of the fleſh, yet to wil is preſent,
<pb facs="tcp:14467:15"/> and the ſpirit will be willing though <note place="margin">Mat. 26</note> the fleſh be weake, and this is our comfort, the ſpirit doth not onely teach vs what to aske, but maketh interceſſions for vs, with ſighes and <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 26.</note> groanes, which cannot be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="observation">
               <head>The eight and laſt leſſon, to learne to pray aright is the neceſsity of <note place="margin">The ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of prayer.</note> 
                  <hi>prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr although this be the laſt, yet it is not the leaſt: for this well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Circū∣ſtance. </seg>8</label> will make vs diligent to learne all the former; I meane how neceſſary prayer is for all Chriſtians, and eſpecially for this laſt age of the world wherin we liue: if we obſerue but the time, it is in the laſt dayes, wherein Satans mallice is ſo much the more increaſed: by howmuch the more his time is diminiſhed, the
<pb facs="tcp:14467:15"/> place wherein we liue, beeing the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>We haue</hi> 3. <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the world, the fleſh, and the deuill.</hi>
                  </note> place where our enimy hath many and great partakers: the fleſh &amp; the diuell are two maine captaines, the world <note n="*" place="margin">I mean the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of the world</note> are the ſouldiers, which are ſeruant to both. If therefore we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the pollicie of our arche enimy Satan: his rage, his watchfulneſſe, his ſtrength, yea the world, which are at his command: and on the other ſide, behold the fleſh, which euer giueth vs battell at home, as alſo the fraile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our owne fleſh, and weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our owne nature: how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able it is to withſtand him, if theſe things were conſidered, they would keepe vs, not onely from ſleeping in ſo great a ieopardy, but to bee watchfull, and call by prayer to God for mercy: (the which if we doe) wee ſhall make him and his great armie to fly. So ſaith <hi>Iames</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:16"/> the bleſſed Apoſtle, <hi>Reſiſt the Deuill, and he will flye from thee.</hi> God giue vs faith, and loue in him: ſo ſhall we be more then conquerors.</p>
               <p>Thus louing brother thou ſeeſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt, who to pray vnto, not to <note place="margin">1. <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</hi>
                  </note> falſe Gods, as Heathens doe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by whom and through whome, to offer vp our yrayers, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</hi>
                  </note> by the virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or any ſaint as the Papiſts doe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, what to pray for, not <note place="margin">3. <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts &amp; world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</hi>
                  </note> with <hi>Balaam,</hi> altogether to ſet our mindes on mony, nor with carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts for worldly pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the cauſes that moue <note place="margin">4. <hi>We muſt learne this leſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before our prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers can be heard.</hi>
                  </note> vs to prayer, which is the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of prayer. From which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue cauſes, we learne theſe leſſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt to pray in obedience to Gods commandement.</p>
               <p>Secondly, with faith in his promiſes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:16"/>
               <p> Thirdly, in humilitie of ſpirit: then ſhall we be ſure to receaue a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, where to pray, not like <note place="margin">5. <hi>Iewes, Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts.</hi>
                  </note> Iewes, no where but in the temple: nor like Browniſts neuer in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but pray thou without any ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious conceit of the place, lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp pure hands to God.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, when, and how long to <note place="margin">6. <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſers.</hi>
                  </note> pray, continually, not with tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers to vſe holy exerciſes, only when religion bringeth gaine &amp; pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Seuenthly, with what affection to <note place="margin">7. <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicean like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors.</hi>
                  </note> pray, not like our <hi>Laodician</hi> profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, who pray with ſuch zeale, that they can ſay nothing, if you take their booke from them: elſe, when they read their prayer, they be halfe a ſleepe before it be ended.</p>
               <p>8. Not to liue idlely as <hi>Dauid</hi> did. <note place="margin">8. <hi>Secure Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
                  </note> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. 12. 3. nor to ſleepe as <hi>Ionah</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:17"/> and <hi>Peter</hi> did, <hi>Math.</hi> 26. 40. for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan is watchfull, and goeth about ſeeking continually whome he may deuoure.</p>
               <p>Theſe obſeruations I thought good to ſet downe for thy better vnderſtanding of the Lords prayer, becauſe therein; I purpoſe to be very briefe, ſetting downe ſuch doctrins, as naturally ariſe from the true ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of the words in the text: the holy and ancient Fathers haue <note place="margin">Forma eſt per qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> res eſt quod eſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit Ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: in dial:</note> called it, <hi>formula precationum,</hi> the forme of prayers: and Logitians ſay, <hi>forma dat eſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſurely this holy Prayer is the patterne, whereby wee may frame our prayers: and if they be not agreeable to this prayer, they be no lawfull prayers.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="exposition">
            <pb facs="tcp:14467:17"/>
            <head>The holy prayer of <hi>our Sauiour.</hi>
            </head>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mathew 6. Chap. verſe, 9.</bibl> 
               <hi>OVr father which art in heauen, halowed be thy name. Thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome come. Thy will be done as in heauen ſo alſo in earth. Giue vs this day our daylie, or continuall bread. And forgiue vs our debts, as we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue our debters. And lead vs not into temptation, but deliuer vs from euill for thine is that kingdome, the power and the glory, for euer and euer, Amen.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>VVHich prayer I deuide into foure parts: into a preface, in theſe wordes, <hi>Our Father which</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:18"/> 
               <hi>art in heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, into ſix petitions, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of three belong vnto God, and three vnto vs.</p>
            <p>The three that belong vnto God, are in theſe wordes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Halowed be thy name.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thy kingdome come.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thy will be done, as in heauen ſo alſo in earth.</p>
            <p>The latter 3. which concerne vs are, 1. Giue vs this day our daylie or continuall bread. 2. And forgiue vs our debts as we forgiue our deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. And lead vs not into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but deliuer vs from euil. 3. Part into a concluſion, for thine is that kingdome, the power &amp; the glory. 4. Part the ſeale of faith, Amen.</p>
            <p>The firſt part of the praier, which is the preface, I deuide into 4. Branches.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14467:18"/>
            <p> Firſt, that God is a father.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that he is our father.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that he is.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the place which is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, that God is a father, it needes no proofe, the ſcriptures are ſo manifeſt, &amp; we are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by our Chriſtian faith, to beleeue that God is a father almighty, in this generall ſence he is the father of good, and bad. But in a more pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar ſence, he is our father, both by creation &amp; adoption, and this doth the Prophet tell the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and in them vs: that we ought not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paie God, for ſo high &amp; marue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous workes, with ingratitude. <hi>Do</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 6.</note> 
               <hi>ye ſo reward the Lord, O ye fooliſh peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and vnwiſe? is not he thy father that bought thee, and that made thee:</hi> alſo <note place="margin">Iſai. 63. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaijah</hi> ſaith, <hi>doubtleſſe, thou art our</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:19"/> 
               <hi>father though</hi> Abraham <hi>know vs not, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>be ignorant of vs: yet thou art our father, and our redeemer, thy name is for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>Obiection.</head>
               <p>CHriſt calleth God, father: is he therefore his father, as he is ours?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwere.</head>
               <p>NO: For he is our father by his creating, and adopting vs in Chriſt. But he is Chriſtes father, <note place="margin">Nota. ☞</note> by eternall generation, he the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſonne of God: but wee by grace. Therefore well did he euer make this diſtinction. I thanke thee ô my father, for ſo hee is in the moſt peculier manner. Alſo, where he ſaith, I go to my father &amp; your father, &amp; my God, and your God.
<pb facs="tcp:14467:19"/> What doth he teach, but that God is his father by eternall generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ours by adoption?</p>
               <p>Now from this word <hi>Father,</hi> let vs learne fiue leſſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, let vs learne to pray in faith. For ſaith <hi>Theophilact,</hi> faith is the very foundation of prayer, and he <note place="margin">1. <hi>Of ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in his promiſes.</hi>
                  </note> goeth further, and ſaith. <hi>Niſi enim crediderit homo, quòd hoc quòd petet accepturus eſt, in ſuam vtilitatem, vanaeſt oratio, quam facit.</hi> Except a <note place="margin">2. <hi>Of our loue.</hi>
                  </note> man beleeue he ſhall receaue that <note place="margin">3. <hi>Of our honoring him.</hi>
                  </note> which hee ſhall aske for his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, that prayer which hee dooth make is vaine. The very worde in <note place="margin">4. <hi>Of feare to his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie.</hi>
                  </note> the originall which is <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>The word</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>put<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth vs in mind.</hi>
                  </note> AB of ABAH to will, it ſheweth, that God willeth our good. And what will a father deny his ſonne, <note place="margin">5. <hi>Of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience &amp; dutie.</hi> Mat. 7. 7</note> that is for his good, ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour: yea ſaith the Lorde, <hi>can a</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:20"/> 
                  <hi>woman forget her childe, and not haue compaſsion on the ſonne of her wombe? though it could be, yet, will I not forget thee,</hi> ſaith the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it teacheth vs to haue a louing affection, when we come to appeare before a mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not as a ſeuere Iudge, therefore ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> (and with him let vs ſay,) <hi>My ſoule thirſteth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 42.</note> 
                  <hi>after the liuing God: when ſhall I come to appeare before the preſence of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly the name <hi>Father,</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs honor. <hi>If I be your Father,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 1.</note> (ſaith God,) <hi>where is my honor?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Feare, <hi>If yee call him</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Father, which without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, iudgeth euery man according to his workes: paſſe the time of your dwelling in feare.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:20"/>
               <p> Fiftly, obedience. <hi>As obedient children faſhion not your ſelues, to the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>former luſtes of ignorance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, this word <hi>Father:</hi> telleth our conſciences, that God is apea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for our ſinnes: and that Chriſt hath fully ſatiſfied his fathers wrath for vs, &amp; ſo we are not only friendes, but alſo coheires with Chriſt: &amp; therefore the ſpirit bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs to call God, (ABBA) father: herein is the great loue, of our mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull father, maruelouſly ſet forth euen in this, that when we were <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 8. 9.</note> yet ſinners, he ſent his ſonne to die for vs. How much more being iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by his bloud, we ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and ſeeing he hath giuen vs Chriſt, how ſhall he not giue vs all things?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>(O Chriſtian)</hi> remember thy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Applica∣tion. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <note place="margin">☞</note> God hath beene twiſe a father
<pb facs="tcp:14467:21"/> to thee: but thou not once wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the name of a ſonne.</p>
               <p>Thus much of the firſt worde <hi>Father:</hi> now for the AFFIX, <hi>[our] I</hi> haue ſhewed before how God is our Father, both by creation and adoption. It followeth to ſet downe, what leſſons wee may learne from this worde <hi>[our,]</hi> which are in number foure.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it teacheth vs charity: for <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">The vſe. </seg>1</label> loue ſeeketh not her owne, but we muſt ſeeke to edifie one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to be like minded one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another, to pray one for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. Therefore dooth Chriſt teach vs, to pray one for another, ſaying, <hi>Our Father,</hi> not <hi>my Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, it doth teach vs, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in ſaith and doctrine with our brethren.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:21"/>
               <p> Thirdly, it teacheth vs humility, to ſay with <hi>Peter,</hi> there is no re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpect <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of perſons with God. And with <hi>Paul,</hi> there is neither <hi>Iewe,</hi> nor <hi>Graecian,</hi> bond, nor free, male, nor female, but wee are all one in Chriſt. Therefore ſaid <hi>Iob, If I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned the iudgement of my ſeruant,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 31. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>when he contended with me: what then ſhall I do, when God ſtandeth vp and viſiteth me? what then ſhall I anſwere?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, it teacheth vs to beware <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> of Sectes and Sciſmatickes, which haue indeed the ſpirite of <hi>Babell,</hi> ſaying, <hi>I am holyer then thee, ſtand from me:</hi> or with the proud Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſie, <hi>I thanke thee Lord, I am not like this Publican.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:22"/>
               <head>The third part of the Preface.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Which art.</head>
                  <p>FOr the firſt word, <hi>Which</hi> (SHE) an abſtract of ASHER, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue, of the roote of the verbe <hi>ASHAR,</hi> of which commeth alſo ASHRE: <hi>Bleſſed, or bleſsings,</hi> giuing vs to vnderſtand thus much, that God is the fountaine whence all bleſſings come. And if we be bleſſed, it is by receiuing it from God, for when God and wee are relatiues. I meane when we are his ſonnes in Chriſt, then doth he impart of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings vnto vs, as ASHRE NES VI <note place="margin">Pſal. 32. 1.</note> PESHANG, <hi>Bleſſed is he whoſe ſinne is forgiuen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:22"/>
                  <head>Art.</head>
                  <p>THis word <hi>(Art)</hi> is not in the originall, but is neceſſarily <note place="margin">יהוה</note> vnderſtood, and this adiunct of <note place="margin">Future. י Preterp. ה Preſent. ו</note> time in the Preſent-tenſe, yea in all tenſes, agreeth to God euermore, as the learned well know. The let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the name <note n="*" place="margin">Theo. Beza in Apoc. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Iehouah</hi> doe <note place="margin">Reuel. 1. 14.</note> note to vs, as much, as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Apocalips: <hi>Which is, which was, and which is to come.</hi> The Preſent, Preter-perfect, and the Future tenſe.</p>
                  <p>The conſideration of this eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrin. </seg>
                     </label> of God, ſtrengtheneth vs in faith, if we obſerue the Apoſtles words, all the promiſes of God in Chriſt, are <hi>Yea,</hi> and <hi>Amen. With God there is no ſhadowe, nor vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of change: for whome he loueth, he loueth to the end.</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14467:23"/> 
                     <hi>Ieſus Chriſt yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame is for euer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The vſe of this is, that we ſhould not wauer in faith, nor be incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                     </label> in religion, but faithfull in all our promiſes, then haue we a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>be faithfull vnto death, and I will giue thee the crowne of life.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>In Heauen.</head>
                  <p>AS, in the firſt word of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> we are taught that God is our father: therefore willing to heare vs. So in this laſt word <hi>(hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen)</hi> we are put in minde of his might, that he is able to helpe vs. <note place="margin">Pſal. 99. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>(Dauid</hi> ſaith) <hi>the Lord is great in Sion, he is high aboue all people.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>My father is greater</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>then I, and none is able to take my</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14467:23"/> 
                     <hi>ſheepe out of his hands: therfore feare not Satans ſubtiltie, nor his childrens tirranie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, we muſt not admit <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> any baſe, or earthly conceit of our father in heauen: for the Prophet <hi>Iſaijah</hi> ſaith, <hi>Gods thoughts are not our thoughts: neither are his wayes our wayes.</hi> But as the heauens, are higher then the earth: ſo are his wayes, higher then our wayes.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the place heauen, muſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> teach vs, that when we come to ſpeake to God by prayer: our mindes muſt not be drawne away with earthly matters, or worldly affaires: for we muſt conſider that we are in the preſence of one, that is ſo infinit in maieſty, that he fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth both heauen and earth, yea this glorious God, maketh the
<pb facs="tcp:14467:24"/> thunder to be at his command, and his voice breaketh the <hi>Ceders</hi> of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banus.</hi> Therefore with <hi>Moſes</hi> let vs <note place="margin">Exo. 34. 8. Pſal. 95. <hi>Kneeling ſeemly in prayer.</hi>
                     </note> bow downe to the earth when we worſhip, alſo with <hi>Dauid</hi> bow downe and kneele, and with great reuerence to God, let vs ſay, with the <hi>Publican.</hi> I am not worthy to looke vp to heauen. With <hi>Dauid</hi> let vs cry, I will lift vp my ſoule vnto thee.</p>
                  <p>Whereas it is ſaid <hi>(Which art in heauen)</hi> that doth not contradict the other place of ſcripture: where God ſaith, the heauen of heauens cannot containe me, how then will yee build a houſe for mee to dwell in? for Gods omnipotencie is euery where: ſo ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 139</note> whether ſhall I go from thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, if I take the winges of the
<pb facs="tcp:14467:24"/> morning, and fly to the vttermoſt part of the world: yea in the deepe, and in hell, alſo there art thou. But as the ſoule is ſaid to be in the head and heart: ſo Gods ſeate is in heauen, and that is as it were his <note n="†" place="margin">Auſtin.</note> temple, ſaith an aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent father, yet is he reſident in all places: euen as the ſoule is in all the parts of mans body, but hath chiefeſt ſeate in the head and hart: ſo God is in all places, but hath his temple, and doth moſt manifeſt his glory in heauen.</p>
                  <p>Laſtlye, it comforteth the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                     </label> of God, to thinke of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: ſeeing God hath promiſed <note place="margin">The laſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the word heauen.</note> that they ſhall be inheritours of ſo glorious a place, which Chriſt hath purchaſed for them. This made all the fathers to behaue themſelues like ſtrangers here, it made <hi>Paule</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 11</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14467:25"/> ſay, he had fought a good fight (though bitter to the fleſh) becauſe ſaith he, is layd vp for me a crowne of glory. Alſo in another place he ſaith, I ſuppoſe that all the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this life, are not worthy the ioyes, that ſhall be reuealed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="petitions">
            <head>Now follow the petitions.</head>
            <div n="1" type="petition">
               <head>Hallowed be thy name.</head>
               <p>VVHich Petition hath two <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Peti∣tion. </seg>1</label> parts, principally to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as.</p>
               <p>Firſt, what is meant by the name of God, in this place. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, what it is to halow <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the ſame.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, the glorious name of God, who can fully expreſſe
<pb facs="tcp:14467:25"/> What is his name, or what is his ſonnes name, ſaith <hi>Agur</hi> the ſonne <note place="margin">Pro. 30. 4.</note> of <hi>Iakeh.</hi> But it hath pleaſed the Holy and Higheſt, to condiſcend to our weake capacities, and in mercy to call himſelfe, by ſuch meanes: as either note to vs his eſſence, as 1. <hi>Iehouah,</hi> 2. <hi>Ehieh,</hi> 3. <hi>Iah,</hi> or his preſence and power, as, 4. <hi>El,</hi> 5. <hi>Eloah,</hi> 6. <hi>Elohim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iehouah,</hi> denoteth vnto vs the <note place="margin">יהוה</note> eſſence of God, euen, that one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Eſſence, which hath beene from all Eternitie: is, and ſhall be, without any change, for euer, and for euer, the vſe of this, is handled before in the worde <hi>Art.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ehieh,</hi> is of the ſame roote that <note place="margin">אהיה</note> 
                  <hi>Iehouah</hi> is, it ſignifieth, <hi>I will be,</hi> The ſonne of God being <hi>Iehouah,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:26"/> equall to the father: appearing to <note place="margin">Exod. 3. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaide vnto him, thou ſhalt go and tell the children of <hi>Iſraell, I will be</hi> hath ſent me vnto you. Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying indeed <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Saith Doctor</hi> Forſter.</note> that he it was, that was to be come man, who was promiſed to <hi>Adam,</hi> and their father <hi>Abraham:</hi> euen God, ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then all the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> who ſhould breake the head of the ſerpent, and deſtroy him of his might.</p>
               <p>This true IEHOVAH called himſelfe EHIEH to <hi>Moſes,</hi> but when he had taken our nature vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and was conſtituted in the miniſtry, &amp; worke of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then he that before ſaid to the children of <hi>Iſraell, I will be,</hi> ſayd <hi>I am, Ihon</hi> 8. 17. <hi>Before Abraham</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 8. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>was, I am.</hi> Yea as ſoone as hee had ſayde to <hi>Iudas</hi> and his company,
<pb facs="tcp:14467:26"/> 
                  <hi>I am he.)</hi> They fell backward. <note place="margin">Iohn. 8. 58.</note> Therefore let me conclude this, with this exhortation of our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <note place="margin">Ioh. 18. 5.</note> to his Apoſtles, beleeue yee in GOD, beleeue alſo in Ieſus <note place="margin">Ioh. 14. 1. 2.</note> Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The third name, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth the eſſence of God, is <note place="margin">יה</note> IAH, an abſtract of IEHOVAH: ſignyfying Chriſt humbled and abaſed in the fleſh.</p>
               <p>And as E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſheweth the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, in his might and gouernement with ELOAH. So doth IAH denote to vs the eſſence of God, as well as IEHOVAH.</p>
               <p>As you may reade in the 146. <hi>Pſal.</hi> In which the office of Chriſt is very plainelye ſet foorth: to bee the Creator of the worlde, and faithfull in his promiſes, who feedeth the hungrye, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſeth
<pb facs="tcp:14467:27"/> priſoners, giueth ſight to the blinde, raiſeth the crooked, loueth the righteous, keepeth them that are deſtitute of worldly ſuccour, releeues fatherleſſe and widdows: and ouerthroweth the way of the wicked. For he came to deſtroy ſinne, and therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> in this place ſaith further, bleſſed is he, that hath the God of <hi>Iacob</hi> for his helpe: and ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vp this <hi>Pſalme</hi> with HALLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LV-IAH.</p>
               <p>And that this is ſpoken of Chriſt: will more plainely appeare, when the new teſtament is compared with this <hi>Pſalme.</hi> Euen the workes of Chriſt, which he did amongſt the Iewes, as he himſelfe ſaid, if ye will not beleeue mee, becauſe the Prophets beare witneſſe of me: yet beleeue for the very workes ſake.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:27"/>
               <p> Alſo he ſaith, if I had not done workes amongſt them, that no man could doe, then had they not ſinne, but now are they without excuſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore when <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> ſent his diſciples to Chriſt: for the inſtructing of them in the faith of the true <hi>Meſsiah.</hi> Our ſauiour had recourſe to this, 146. <hi>pſal.</hi> and ſaid, go tell <hi>Iohn:</hi> the blind ſee, the lame are made whole, the dead are rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp, the deafe heare, the poore <note place="margin">Luk. 7. 22.</note> receiue the goſpell, and bleſſed is he that is not offended in mee. And the children of God, which were deliuered from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage <note n="*" place="margin">For he was Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict the church.</note> of ſinne, the tyrannye of Sathan † and the Pope, by Chriſt: ſing HALLELV-IAH, which is in Engliſh, <hi>prayſe yee the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:28"/>
               <p> Let vs therefore in our prayers, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">The vſe. </seg>
                  </label> and in all our ſonges of reioycing: alſo praiſe God for our deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, from the ſlauery of ſinne and Satan. And for our happye deliueraunce from Romiſh <hi>Babell:</hi> God giuing vs free liberty, to prayſe him in the congregation: yea to pay the praiſes of God with the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> in <hi>pſalme.</hi> 56. 12. <note place="margin">יהוה אהיה יה</note> Becauſe hee hath deliuered our life from death, and our feete from falling, <hi>prayſed be</hi> IAH, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">ab היה eſſe.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The three names of God, that put vs in minde of his preſence and power be theſe, EL, ELOAH and ELOHIM, which are all of one ſignification: declaring to vs, that our God is ſtrong, againſt whome, there is no reſiſtance.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:28"/>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God.</note> Therefore what greater comfort <note place="margin">אל אלוה אלהים Fortis victor.</note> can a Chriſtian haue then this: <hi>The Lorde is on my ſide, I willnot feare what man can doe vnto mee. For the mighty God is my refuge, euen the God of</hi> Iacob, <hi>is my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">God is terrible to the wicked.</note> And what a terror is it to the wicked, that God euen the ſtrong one, is againſt them, ready to ſend them to vtter confuſion when it pleaſeth him: bee they neuer ſo ſtrong and mighty here?</p>
               <p>Therfore a little, is better to the Godlye: then much ſpoyles, and the great wealth of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. For they ſtand in ſlipperye places.</p>
               <p>ELOHIM, alſo importeth the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <note place="margin">Elohim <hi>the plural of</hi> Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah:</note> when it is either ioyned with a verbe of the ſinguler number,
<pb facs="tcp:14467:29"/> as <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>In the beginning, Gods, he</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">When it impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Trinitie.</note> 
                  <hi>made heauen and earth.</hi> And ELO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HIM he ſayd, <hi>Let there be light.</hi> And againe, ELOHIM ſaid, <hi>Let vs make man:</hi> with many ſuch like places, as <hi>Deuter.</hi> 10. <hi>Exod.</hi> 8. and when this Nowne Plurall is ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a Relatiue ſingular, as <hi>Ioſu.</hi> 24. but moſt liuely doth the 35. <hi>Chapter</hi> and 7. <hi>verſe</hi> of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> expreſſe the Trinitie. <hi>And</hi> Iacob <hi>built there an Alter, and called the name of the place</hi> ELDETHEL, <hi>becauſe,</hi> (ſaith he) KI SHAM NIGLV ELAV HA ELOHIM. <hi>Quia reuclati ſunt ad eum dij,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Gods were there reuealed vnto him: where it importeth the Trinitie, and moſt liuely ſheweth the three perſons in the Deity.</p>
               <p>Firſt, ELOHIM importeth the <note place="margin">In how many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces this worde is vſed in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> Trinitie, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>Ioſu.</hi> 24. <hi>Gen.</hi> 35. 7.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:29"/>
               <p> Secondly, this name is giuen to falſe Gods, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 7.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, to men in office, as <hi>Deut</hi> 1. Alſo where God ſaith to <hi>Moſes, I haue made thee</hi> Pharaohs <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, to Angels, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>GOD, alſo calleth himſelfe <note place="margin">שדי <hi>God v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this name for the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thning of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in faith and obedience as,</hi> Gen. 17.</note> SHADDI, which ſignifieth <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent, Al-ſufficient.</hi> Some lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned deriue this word of SHAEL, which in the Hebrew tongue ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth <hi>a womans Breſt, or Pap:</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vs thus much: that as the mother doth nouriſh and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, her young childe, by the milke of her breſts: Euen ſo doth the Lord his children, with his grace and louing kindneſſe. <note place="margin">Gen. 28</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">S. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom.</note> Other learned ſay, it is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound word of SHE, the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue,
<pb facs="tcp:14467:30"/> and DAI, which ſignifieth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundancy, ſufficiencie, and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for he not onely aboundeth with all good things himſelfe: but <note place="margin">Iohn. 1. 14. 16.</note> alſo giueth aboundantly to all. For of his fulneſſe wee receiue <note place="margin">Tim: 6. 17.</note> grace for grace. And therefore the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> willeth men not to truſt in vncertaine riches: but in God that giueth aboundantly to all. Yea, this word SHADDAI doth not only ſignifie, that God is Almightie and Al-ſufficient, but that he affecteth all things in all creatures, to which ſence, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alludes, when he ſaith, <hi>God</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Act. 17 24. 5. 6. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>that made the worlde, and all things that are therein, ſeeing that he is Lorde of Heauen and Earth: dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not in temples made with hands,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>neither is worſhipped with mens hands, as though he needed any things,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:30"/> 
                  <hi>ſeeing he giueth to all, breath, and life, and all things. And hath made of one bloud, all mankinde, to dwell on all the face of the earth. And hath aſsigned the times, which were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained before: and bonds of their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations, that they ſhould ſeeeke the Lorde: if ſo be they might haue gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped after him, and founde him, though doubtleſſe hee is not farre from euery one of vs. For in him wee liue, and mooue, and haue our being.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo the Apoſtle ſaith to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities of operations: But God is the ſame that worketh all in all.</p>
               <p>And in the ſame chapter, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing repeated diuerſe and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye giftes, hee ſaith, all theſe things worketh euen the ſelfe ſame
<pb facs="tcp:14467:31"/> ſpirit diſtributing to euery man, ſeuerally as he will: for of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, wiſedome and bounty, all men and creatures in the world, haue their being, moouing, and liuing, receiuing all from his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall treaſury. Theſe and ſuch like names, bring moſt heauenly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation, yea and conſolation, to the children of God, who are deſirous to know their fathers name: ſo farre forth as he is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it ſhall be knowne, and as he hath reuealed it vnto vs, in his word. Many and moſt ſinguler (for heauenly comfort,) are the attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of God, in the ſcriptures: as Iuſt, mercifull, prudent, wiſe, true, and holy: theſe and many ſuch like, ſhew the properties that be in God. Which dooth not onely comfort vs in affliction, but alſo
<pb facs="tcp:14467:31"/> leade forwarde, our affections to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes perfection. Therefore, theſe names are not to be vſed of vs at our pleaſure: but with all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, leaſt in ſteade of halow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we prophaine the name of God; But alas, we ſtay not in this ſinne: but euen many times, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the name of God. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuch as remaine in this deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſinne, cannot haue any aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that, that which they pray for, ſhall be granted.</p>
               <p>For Godly his Prophets hath ſayd, hee will not here the praiers of ſuch. Yea, thoſe that be ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners <note place="margin">Ier. 17. 16.</note> of God, and his word, hath God ſaid, they ſhall call vpon me, <note place="margin">Ezek. 8. 18.</note> when affliction, and anguiſh ſhall <note place="margin">Prou. 1. 28.</note> fall on them: but I will not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare. Alſo againſt vayne bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 29.</note> hath the Lorde ſayde, that
<pb facs="tcp:14467:32"/> 
                  <hi>when they crye he will be a farre of. Pro.</hi> 15. 29. How much more then, when the blaſphemers cryeth: for blaſphemers are farre from a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, when they call to God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they delighte in curſing, and indeede that is their portion from the Lord, <hi>Zach.</hi> 5. 13. 4. euen curſes and woes a whole booke full, and the Wiſe man ſaith thus, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 23. 9.</p>
               <p>Accuſtome not thy ſelfe to ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: <note place="margin">Eccl. 23. 9.</note> (for therein is many falles,) neither take for accuſtome the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Alſo</hi> Exo. 20. 7.</note> of the holy one: (for thou ſhalt not be vnpuniſhed for ſuch things.) <note place="margin">cha. 27. 15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>For as a ſeruant which is often <note place="margin">Math. 5. 33.</note> puniſhed cannot be without ſome ſcar, ſo he that ſweareth, &amp; nameth God continually, ſhal not be fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and a man that vſeth much
<pb facs="tcp:14467:32"/> ſwearing, ſhall be filled with wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, and the plague ſhall neuer go from his houſe: when he ſhall offend, his fault ſhall be vpon him, and if he knowledge not his ſinne, he maketh a double offence: Yea, if he ſweare in vaine, he ſhall not be innocent, but his houſe ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of plagues. Thinke vpon this, yee that vſe ſwearing: and learne to halow Gods name, els yee but mock God, in ſaying (halowed be thy name) and yet profane his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred name: bind not two ſinnes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gather for euen in one ſhalt thou not go vnpuniſhed.</p>
               <p>And here in this petition by <note place="margin">What is here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, by name.</note> 
                  <hi>name,</hi> I vnderſtand the power of God, as to caſt out deuils in the name of Chriſt: it was to do it in the power and vertue of Chriſt.
<pb facs="tcp:14467:33"/> Alſo, where the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>At the name of Ieſus euery knee ſhall bow,</hi> &amp;c. is meant that euery crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhall be ſubiect to the power of Chriſt. Therefore we will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that man bleſſed, whoſe ſtrength is <hi>Iehouah</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Prou: 18. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>For the name of the Lord,</hi> is a ſtrong tower, the <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous runne to it and are exalted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, note whereas we ſay <note place="margin">What is meant by halowing the name of God in this place</note> halowed be thy name. We do not meane that God, or his name, is vnholy in it ſelfe: but as it is ſaid of wiſedome which is moſt iuſt, that ſhee is iuſtified of her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: (becauſe they ſo account <note place="margin">Sebuſ: Mun.</note> his, and acknowledge her:) ſo heere meane wee that by the halowing of Gods name, that hee would graunt vs to confeſſe, acknowledge, honour, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bay this holye name of his, and
<pb facs="tcp:14467:33"/> this is the halowing of the name of God.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore wee learne from <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">The vſe. </seg>
                  </label> hence, that both by faith &amp; obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in knowledge &amp; practiſe, we muſt ſanctifie the name of God.</p>
               <p>Alſo, with ſoule and body, in word and thought, whatſoeuer yee doe in word or deede, do all to the glory of God, ſaith <hi>Paule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, let vs take heede, that whatſoeuer we aske, it may bee to Gods glory, and that we preferre the glory of God, before any other thing in the world whatſoeuer, and then haue we promiſe to be heard.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="petition">
               <head>The 2. petition,</head>
               <q>Let thy Kingdome come.</q>
               <p>THe kingdome of God is three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:34"/>
                  <item>1. His kingdome of power.</item>
                  <item>2. His kingdome of grace.</item>
                  <item>3. His kingdome of glory.</item>
               </list>
               <p>For the firſt, that is his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of power, whereby he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all his creatures to ſerue him: as well bad as good, that is not meant in this place, for God will neuer leſſen and take away this his authority: Therefore ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> whatſoeuer it pleaſed the Lord, that did he in heauen, in earth, in the ſea, and in all deepes. But in this place we meane the kingdome of grace, that God would raigne in our hartes, &amp; that he would put to flight, all our old ſinnes, both originall, and actuall: that our bodyes might be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red fit temples for the holy ghoſt, for this kingdome is neither meat, nor drinke: but righteouſneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:14467:34"/> peace, and ioy in the holye ghoſt. For this kingdome, comes not by obſeruation; but it muſt be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered within. And ſaith that god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Father <hi>Theophilact. Nam ſi quempiam videris, quaſi abſque carne viuere vitam Euangelicam, an non diceres, quod regnum coelorum iam habet?</hi> for if thou ſhalt ſee any man to liue an Euangelicall life, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not in the fleſh, wilt thou not ſay, that he hath already the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God?</p>
               <p>And in another place he ſaith, to beleeue aright, and to walke ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, is called to be worthy our vocation, which is indeede to be ſubiects of this kingdome. And the ſame author ſaith, on <hi>Mat. chap.</hi> 23. vppon theſe wordes, <hi>the Scribes and the Phariſes would neither enter into the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God nor ſuffer other,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:35"/> It is, ſaith he, <hi>they would neither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in</hi> Chriſt, <hi>nor yet ſuffer others that would.</hi> In this petition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee pray, that God would raigne in our hearts, by a true and a liuely faith. And if we vnfained<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie beleeue, we haue the promiſes of this life, and of that, which is to come. For ſaith Chriſt: <hi>Seeke firſt the kingdome of God, and the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe thereof, and all other things ſhall be caſt vnto you.</hi> Alſo note, that in this petition, we pray for the meanes to beget faith, which is preaching, alſo for the right vſe of the Sacraments, which is a meanes to ſtrengthen our faith: and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Magiſtrates, for to keepe the <note n="*" place="margin">Which is the Church.</note> body in order: and how can any good Chriſtian, but remember our good Prince in his prayers. Praiſing God for her, and praying
<pb facs="tcp:14467:35"/> him to prolong her dayes, to raigne long amongſt vs here, and after this life, with God for euer.</p>
               <p>The third kingdome, is the kingdome of glorie, the ſtate of happineſſe after this life, which we in deed pray for in this petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but it is mediatly, as being firſt, members of the kingdome of grace: for whome God rules, <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> them he ſanctifieth, and whome hee ſanctifieth, them alſo he iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, and whome he iuſtifieth, them alſo he will glorifie.</p>
               <div type="application">
                  <head>Application.</head>
                  <p>But alas, what ſhall we ſay, by ſuch as haue ſuch wauering and vnſtedfaſtneſſe in religion: can they pray in hope to be heard? Surely no, <hi>for ſeeing they haue</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14467:36"/> 
                     <hi>delighted to wander,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and haue not refrained their ſeete: therfore when they faſt, I will not heare</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 14. 10. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>their crie: and when they offer burnt offrings, and oblations, I will not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept them.</hi> Therefore purge your harts, yee wauering minded men, elſe are yee not ſubiects of this kingdome: the admiſſion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto is by faith: and if yee be not ſubiects, God taketh you for his enemies, againſt whome he will execute a heauie iudgement. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19. 2. 7. <hi>Bring hether thoſe mine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, that would not I ſhould</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 19. 27.</note> 
                     <hi>raigne ouer them, and ſlaye them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Oh conſider this, yee that forget God,) <hi>Leaſt I teare you in peeces, and there be none that can deliuer you,</hi> ſaith the Eternall. <hi>But he that offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth praiſes, ſhall glorifie me, and to</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 50. 32.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14467:36"/> 
                     <hi>him that diſpoſeth his waye aright: will I ſhewe the ſaluation of God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="petition">
               <head>The 3. petition.</head>
               <q>Thy will be done, as in heauen, ſo alſo in earth.</q>
               <p>THis petition rightly, and fitly, agreeth with the former: for in the other, we pray that GOD may rule our hearts to beleeue, which cannot be, if we be vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to doe the will of God our heauenly Father. Therefore apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie wee pray in the next place, for the effects of faith, obedience to Gods lawes, in theſe wordes, <hi>Thy will be done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which petition hath two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall parts, that is:</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:37"/>
               <p> Firſt, what the will of God is.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that is not enough to know the ſame, but to doe it.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, the will of God we pray may be done, is his reuealed will in his word. This teacheth vs how precious knowledge is, and that it is a great meanes to make vs able: in ſome good meaſure to doe Gods will, for firſt we muſt know, what is to be done, before we can doe it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it teacheth, that wee muſt not do our owne wils, eyther in prayer, or in any matter of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. For God will be prayed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and ſerued, as he hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his word, and therefore hee ſaith, obedience is better then ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. Wherefore, let vs looke to our feete, before we come to pray: leaſt we offer the ſacrifice of fooles:
<pb facs="tcp:14467:37"/> and let vs learne the will of God. This ſaith Chriſt, is the will of God, to beleeue in him, whome he hath ſent, and the Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith.</p>
               <p>This is the will of God, euen our ſanctification. So that here we ſee, that faith and a holy life, are ioyned together, God requiring the one, of him that hath the other: for indeed they be Relatiues, and S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, <hi>faith that is without workes, is dead.</hi> Yea our ſauiour ſaith, not euery one, that ſaith Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the kingdome of heauen: but he that doth the will of my father, which is in heauen. Therefore, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is truely iuſtified, is in ſome good meaſure ſanctified: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, faith can no more be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good workes, then fire can be
<pb facs="tcp:14467:38"/> without heate.</p>
               <div type="application">
                  <head>The vſe.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, we learne to aske nothing in our prayers, which is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to Gods word.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, we learne to take all croſſes patiently: that with Chriſt we may ſay, not my will, but thine (ô father) be fulfilled.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, we are here taught, to ſtriue towardes perfection, for Gods children haue an earneſt deſire to doe his will. And with <hi>Dauid</hi> to ſay, it is written, <hi>(O Lord)</hi> in the volume of thy booke, that I ſhall doe thy will, O God, and loe I come.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="application">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:38"/>
                  <head>Application.</head>
                  <p>SVch therefore, as deſpiſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and ſet light by the word of God: their prayers will God deſpiſe, for ſaith the Prophet <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Zach. 7. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>as God cried to them:</hi> and they would not here, ſo when they cry he will not here them.</p>
                  <p>But where the worde of the Lord is imbraſed: there the Lord is nigh to vs in all that wee call vppon him for. Yea they that <note place="margin">Deut. 4. 7.</note> keepe Gods commaundements, receiue whatſoeuer they aske, but as for ſuch, as haue no care to doe <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3 22.</note> Gods will, the Lord is farre from them.</p>
                  <p>Therfore (ô man,) if thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt that God ſhould here thy prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 29.</note> when thou calleſt vpon him:
<pb facs="tcp:14467:39"/> heare thou the Lorde, and amend thy wayes: when by his good ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit he calleth vnto thee, els thy prayer is vaine babling. <note place="margin">Pro. 35. 13.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond part of this petition:</head>
               <q>As in heauen ſo alſo in earth.</q>
               <p>THis ſaith one, is no otherwiſe, but as the Angels ſerue thee in heauen: euen ſo ſhould we ſerue thee in earth, with all alacritie and willingneſſe, in all humility and faithfulneſſe. And howſoeuer no Chriſtian can performe ſuch obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in this life: yet this petition teacheth, that we ought to haue a deſire ſo to do.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:39"/>
               <p> From the conſideration of theſe things we learne three profitable leſſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt that God ought to raigne here in our hartes on earth, as well as hee doth in heauen, but ſeeing it is not ſo: how ought we to bee humbled, and caſt downe in our ſelues, when we conſider how diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient we haue beene, to the will of our heauenly father.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it ought to mooue vs, to all poſſible thankfulneſſe, for our redemption, when wee conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this example of the Angels, who were but once created, but we miſerable ſinners put God to a new worke, to redeeme vs by the bloud of his owne ſonne.</p>
               <p>Laſtly it teacheth vs that we ought to loue God, more then the Angels: in as much as wee haue
<pb facs="tcp:14467:40"/> put him to a greater buſines, and haue receiued greater mercies then they: and they which haue much forgiuen them, ought to <note place="margin">Luke. 7.</note> loue much.</p>
               <div type="application">
                  <head>Application.</head>
                  <p>BEhold thy duty (ô man) conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der but the Angels: the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures deſcribe them to haue ſix winges, two to couer their face, by which they ſignifie to vs, that they are not able to looke into the depth of Gods counſailes, they haue two alſo to couer their feete, ſhewing their owne inſufficiencie, and vnworthyneſſe, to ſerue ſo glorious a God, yet haue they two wings alſo about their hart, to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie vnto vs, that with hearty o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, they do the will of God.
<pb facs="tcp:14467:40"/> Therefore, ô ſinfull man, looke to the heauens, and beholde the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, looke into the firmament, behold the Sunne, the Moone, &amp; the ſtarres, yea in the earth alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, times and ſeaſons, all theſe obay Gods will. Therefore ô man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde for whoſe ſake theſe were created, and for whoſe ſake God, equall to the father, thought it no ſcorne to take vnto him our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to be our brother accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh, that hee might condempne ſinne in the fleſh: let vs not therefore walke after the fleſh, but let our conuerſation be in heauen: whether our eldeſt brother is gone before vs, that in his time we may be with our head Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="petition">
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:41"/>
               <head>The 4. petition.</head>
               <q>Giue vs this day our dayly or continuall Bread.</q>
               <q>
                  <hi>O praiſe the Lord of Lords, for his mercie endureth for euer, which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth foode to all fleſh, for his mercie endureth for euer,</hi> 
                  <bibl>Pſal. 136. 2. 25.</bibl>
               </q>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Bread.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">לחם</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>THis word <hi>Bread,</hi> is tooke in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſences in the Scriptures: whereof there are fiue principall.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Firſt, it is taken for bread pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. 18. <hi>Exod.</hi> 25. 30. <hi>Prou.</hi> 28. 19.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Secondly, for bread corne, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 47. 15. <hi>Iob.</hi> 28. 5.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Thirdly, it is neither tooke
<pb facs="tcp:14467:41"/> for bread nor corne, but for <hi>Manna</hi> Exo. 16. 15. <hi>Behold I will raine to you bread fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen.</hi> Alſo Pſal. 105. 40. <hi>he ſatiſfied them with bread from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen:)</hi> which <hi>Manna</hi> was a figure of Chriſt, who is the true bread of heauen, and many of the ancient fathers vnderſtand by <hi>Bread</hi> in this petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is the true bread of life: whom we are to deſire, and pray for, before all other things.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Fourthly, it is tooke for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices <hi>Leuit.</hi> 3. 11. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 7. <note place="margin">What is meant by bread in this peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. Laſtly, it is taken generally, for all things neceſſary for this life, as <hi>Gen</hi> 3. 19. <hi>In the ſweat of thy face, ſhalt thou eate thy bread:</hi> That is thou ſhalt get thy liuing. Alſo in Pſal. 38. 25. <hi>Which giueth food to all fleſh.</hi> Alſo Pro. 30. 8. <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>So doth</hi> Treme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it in his Hebrew catechiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Feed me with food conuenient for me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So likewiſe in this petition, we
<pb facs="tcp:14467:42"/> vnderſtand ſaith <hi>Bucer, Victum qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſcunque</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Bucer in Mat. 6. pag. 62.</note> 
                     <hi>vita praeſens opus habet:</hi> all things that be neceſſary for this life, from which word wee may conſider, the bountifull liberallitie of God, towards all his creatures, but more eſpecially towards man: for whom he both careth and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth. And therefore the Apoſtle in the 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. ſaith. <hi>Truſt not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vncertaine riches, but in God that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to all aboundantly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, this word <hi>Our bread,</hi> doth not import that it is ours by <note n="*" place="margin">Riches are not ours pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, but lent vs, and wee are ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards of them, &amp; muſt giue account for them.</note> deſert, but being got with a good conſcience: not by defrauding of our brother any way, that ſo we may eate our owne bread. The which cannot be, except we liue in a lawfull calling. Oh thou that haſt no calling, or an vnlawfull
<pb facs="tcp:14467:42"/> calling, how canſt thou ſay this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition? Let gameſters, and ſuch as haue no lawfull calling, conſider, in what ſtate they ſtand in, and let them (ſaith the Apoſtle,) rather la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with their hands, for <hi>he that will not labour, let him not eate.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Our continuall or dayly Bread.</head>
                  <p>BY this word <hi>continuall or daylye Bread,</hi> I gather theſe leſſons.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Firſt, that none muſt aske ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or any other thing to ſatiſfie the fleſh withall, for becauſe <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> did neither aske riches, honor, not long life but wiſedome: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord gaue them al to him. So that the like was not vnto <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 1. 12.</note> before nor ſince, for wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, riches, and honor.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Secondly, it teacheth vs, that
<pb facs="tcp:14467:43"/> euery day we muſt come to God by prayer.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Thirdly, theſe words <hi>(daily bread)</hi> or as in <hi>Luk.</hi> 11. <hi>(Bread for the day.)</hi> It teacheth vs this leſſon, not to haue any miſtruſtfulneſſe of Gods promiſes, nor vſe no vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes to get our liuing, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord is faithfull, that hath ſaid, <hi>I will not leaue thee, nor forſake</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 11</note> 
                     <hi>thee.</hi> Yea the ſcriptures ſay; <hi>caſt your care vpon God, for he careth for you:</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> and knoweth whereof yee haue neede before ye aske. Neither will he that clotheth the Lillies, &amp; fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Rauens, ſuffer any of his to want their food. For if God cloath the graſſe of the field, which to day flouriſheth, and to morrow is cut downe. Then much more will he man: whome he hath ſo dearely loued, and ſo dearly bought. And
<pb facs="tcp:14467:43"/> this made <hi>Dauid</hi> ſay: <hi>The Lions ſhal</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 34.</note> 
                     <hi>be hunger bit: but thoſe that feare God, ſhall lacke nothing.</hi> Beleeue we not this (O we of little faith,) are we like the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to tempte God? or are we as incredulous, as the Prince that told the Prophet, though God ſhould <note place="margin">2. Kings 7. 17.</note> make wonders in heauen, yet that great dearth could not be turned into ſuch a plentie, as God by his Prophet tolde it ſhould be? And ſurely infidelitie and vnthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is the cauſe of all wante. Therefore if we would want no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, let vs truſt God (ô we of lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle faith,) then, <hi>fides Famem non ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met:</hi> Faith feareth not Dearth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Giue.</head>
                  <p>So the word in the <hi>originall,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>to giue, or beſtow freely.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 4. 7.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:44"/>
                  <p> From which, we learne theſe leſſons. <note place="margin">Pro. 23. 26.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, that all we haue, commeth <note place="margin">Pſ. 104.</note> from God, and therefore whether <note place="margin">Gen. 43 14.</note> we haue little or much: we muſt giue him praiſe for the ſame. <note place="margin">Iſa. 9. 6.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, that man may toyle and labour, and if God giue not a bleſſing all is in vaine, for ſaith <hi>Dauid, promotion is neither from the eaſt nor from the weſt: but of the Lord.</hi> Therefore (ô rich man,) ſeeing thou haſt nothing of thy ſelfe: but all that thou haſt, thou haſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, boaſt not of it, as if thou hadſt not receiued it, neither be thou proud, of that which is not thine owne.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>To vs.</head>
                  <p>BY this, we learne euery one, to ſeeke anothers good, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:14467:44"/> man to pray for the good of his brother. Not like <hi>Ahab,</hi> neuer to be at reſt, till we haue got <hi>Naboths</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Iob. 31. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>vineyarde.</hi> But with <hi>Iob,</hi> not to eat our morſelles alone, but the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe to eate with vs: neither to ſee any periſh for want of clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but to couer them, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lorde ſhall call vs to account for theſe earthly riches: we may be found faithfull ſtewards<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; hauing beene faithfull in ſmall matters, he <note n="*" place="margin">The old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but true di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie teacheth, one for another, and God for vs all.</note> may make vs rulers ouer greater: ſaying wel done, faithfull ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; true, enter into your maiſters ioy.</p>
                  <div type="application">
                     <head>Application.</head>
                     <p>BVt what ſhall a man ſay to theſe laſt dayes, wherein charity is waxed cold, &amp; men do not relieue, but reuile the poore members of Chriſt, ſhall ſuch men bee heard,
<pb facs="tcp:14467:45"/> when they pray? or doe they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what they pray when they ſay <hi>(Giue vs)</hi> and yet are for no man but themſelues? Surely theſe men are no better, then moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of this heauenly prayer, and therefore, booteleſſe is it for them to call vpon the Lord: For <hi>Salomon</hi> hath told them, they ſhall not be <note place="margin">Pro. 21. 13.</note> hard † yea and he that iniureth the poore, doth as one, that ſacrifiſeth <note n="*" place="margin">Eccle. 34. 21.</note> the ſonne before the fathers eyes. Therefore, if any would haue his prayers hard of God, to whome he is a begger: let him ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy here to his brother. That with hart, as well as with tongue, he may ſay this petition, leaſt there be iudgement mercileſſe, to him that ſheweth no mercy: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <note place="margin">Iam. 2. 13.</note> make they neuer ſo faire a ſhew of religion, all is hipocriſie.
<pb facs="tcp:14467:45"/> 
                        <hi>And God will not here the prayers of hipocrites, Iob.</hi> 27. 9. Wherefore (ô rich men) here the counſaile of <hi>Daniel: Breake of your ſinnes by righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 24.</note> 
                        <hi>and your iniquities, by mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy towardes the poore: and let there be a healing of this errour.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="petition">
               <head>The 5. petition.</head>
               <q>And forgiue vs our debts, euen as we forgiue our debtors.</q>
               <p>LEt vs conſider, that this follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the other petition very fitly, for in the former we begge foode of God, to the end our life might be preſerued: in this we beg remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſins, that we may liue in God. In the former we aske thoſe things which concerne this life:
<pb facs="tcp:14467:46"/> but in theſe two latter, thoſe things which concerne vs here-after. Theſe petitions as all the former, are grounded on Gods promiſes, if we haue a repenting hart. <hi>Their iniquities</hi> (ſaith GOD) <hi>I will</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 31. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>forgiue, and remember their ſinnes no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Forgiue.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Selach <hi>ſignifieth freely to forgiue, as</hi> 1. Ki. 8. 36.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe Firſt word of this petition which is <hi>forgiue,</hi> teacheth vs, that we are ſaued &amp; imputed righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous through faith in <hi>Chriſt</hi> only, <note place="margin">Pſa. 103 2.</note> and without any of our own good <note place="margin">Pſal. 86. &amp; 130. 4</note> workes, for ſaith <hi>Paule, we are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied freely by faith, not of workes,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>we haue the forgiueneſſe of our ſins through his rich grace: for by grace</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>are we ſaued through ſaith, not of our ſelues, it is the gift of god.</hi> Thus was <note place="margin">Rom. 11. 6.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14467:46"/> 
                     <hi>Mary, Peter, and the publican ſaued,</hi> yea, all are ſaued by grace. This muſt teach vs humility, and not to ſay, I thanke thee, ô Lord I am not like this publican: but to ſay with <hi>Paule,</hi> 
                     <note n="†" place="margin">But pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts that ſay they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> merit heauen are the ſucceſſors of the proud Phariſes, and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans ſhall be iuſtified before them.</note> 
                     <hi>Chriſt Ieſus came into the world to ſaue ſinners: of whom I am cheife,</hi> and then if we humble our ſelues, God will exalt vs.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the word, <hi>(forgiue)</hi> teacheth vs, that we ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our ſinnes <hi>to God: that ſo we</hi> may finde mercy, for <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label>
                     <hi>whilſt I helde my tongue my bones conſumed.</hi> Therefore he confeſſed <note place="margin">Pſal. 32.</note> to the Lord his owne wickednes againſt himſelfe, and he forgaue the wickednes of his ſinnes: &amp; <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>though God ſhould kill me, yet wil I truſt in him, &amp; I will reproue my</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Iob. 13. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>wayes in his ſight.</hi> Alſo wiſe <hi>Salomon</hi> giues vs this leſſon, <hi>he that hideth</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14467:47"/> 
                     <hi>his ſinnes, ſhall not proſper, but he that confeſſeth and forſaketh them, he ſhall haue mercy.</hi> Iuſt <hi>Iob,</hi> confeſſed his ſinnes, ſo did <hi>Dauid</hi> and the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall ſonne, alſo the <hi>Publican</hi> and the <hi>theife</hi> on the croſſe.</p>
                  <p>Thus by theſe examples we ſee that confeſſion of ſinnes, muſt go before remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If thy ſinne be pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, then confeſſion to God, may be priuat, but if it be publique, then muſt there bee publique confeſſion, that the Church may take notice of thy true contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, it teacheth vs the great <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> patience of God, in not confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of vs when we haue firſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but ſuffering vs ſo long, and giuing vs ſpace to repent. This patience of God ſaith <hi>Saint Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> ſhould leade vs to repentance,
<pb facs="tcp:14467:47"/> and not to ſay with the foole, <hi>tuſh God ſeeth it not.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>the Lord is full of mercy, and of great goodnes,</hi> but he alſo ſaith, <hi>if a man will not turne, he will bend his bow and whet his ſworde.</hi> And the longer hee deferreth his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the higher he heaueth his hand, the greater will the blow bee.</p>
                  <p>Therefore though God haue but a leaden heele: yet hath he <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> an <hi>Iron ſcepter.</hi> Thus much of the firſt word <hi>forgiue.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Vs, or to vs.</head>
                  <p>BY this word <hi>(vs,)</hi> we are taught to pray for the ſaluation of our brethren, yea of all, if it were Gods will, by the example of <hi>Saint Paule,</hi> who could haue wiſhed to haue
<pb facs="tcp:14467:48"/> beene ſeperate from God, for his countrie mens ſake the <hi>Iewes.</hi> But few go ſo farre with <hi>Paule,</hi> for if they wiſh their friendes any thing, it is rather worldly wealth, honor, and dignity, then the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and increaſe of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all graces, forgetting <hi>Chriſt</hi> his wordes, <hi>what will it profit a man to winne the whole world, and to loſe his owne ſoule?</hi> but this is the frailenes of our fleſh, and ſinnefull nature, to be more prone to earthly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, then feruently to deſire, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly bleſſinges.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Our debts. <note place="margin">Breach of the lawe is debt, which is our ſins.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>INdeede ſinnes are rightly our debtes. Which make vs indeb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto God by tranſgreſſion of his diuine law. Alas, goodneſſe was
<pb facs="tcp:14467:48"/> once ours, but we in our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents loſt the very will of dooing well, how much more the power to do well. So that God now ſaith, <note place="margin">Gen. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>the thoughts of mans heart are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euill.</hi> Therfore ſinnes are right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ours now indeed. The bleſſed Apoſtle Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> ſheweth this, where he prooued that God temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth none to doe euill, but all ſuch temptations are of our ſelues, and <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> he ſaith further, <hi>whence are wars, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and enuyings, are they not euen of your ſelues?</hi> yea the Apoſtle <hi>Paule,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of</hi> Paule <hi>differeth from the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique.</hi>
                     </note> that choſen veſſell, could ſay, <hi>I know in me,</hi> (that is in my ſelfe) <hi>dwelleth no good thing, and howſoeuer to will is preſent with me, yet I finde by the law of God, that I do that which I ſhould not doe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:49"/>
                  <head>Debts.</head>
                  <p>Well may our ſinnes, the breach of the law, be called Debts: tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vs of our neglect of duty, and of our playing the bankrupts, with the graces of the good ſpirit of God, as alſo to bind vs to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat of God, laying before vs the haynouſneſſe of our ſinnes, and the ritch mercy of God in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who when we had nothing to pay, forgaue vs all.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond part of the fift Petition.</head>
               <q>As we forgiue our debters.</q>
               <p>This forgiueneſſe of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, it is a ſure teſtimony, that God in the firſt place hath forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs, and ſo ſaith <hi>Saint Iohn, by</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:49"/> 
                  <hi>this we know, we are tranſlated from death to life, becauſe we loue the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> and Chriſt his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, <hi>be yee mercifull, as your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father is mercifull</hi> O how can they looke for mercy which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in malice, for Chriſt hath ſaid it, (therefore it is true) <hi>With what meaſure you meate to others, it ſhall be meaſured to you againe.</hi> Therefore let not the ſunne go downe on thy wrath: for what knoweſt thou (ô man) whether thou ſhalt liue till to morrow, and if thou ſhouldſt dye in malice, thou dyeſt not in God, for God is loue: In the feare of God conſider this, and firſt be reconciled vnto thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift, for if (ſaith the Wiſeman) one pray, and another curſe, which will God heare. Nay ſuch as bee full of
<pb facs="tcp:14467:50"/> cruelty and reuengement, what in this Petition do they pray for? but this, that Gods curſe and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance might light on them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whoſoeuer thou art, that ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieſt malicious minde to thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: thou art altogether vnfit to ſay this prayer, or any holy prayer. Yea, and God will not heare thee, when thou calleſt vnto him, when thou ſtretcheſt forth thy hands, he will hide his eyes. And though <note place="margin">Iſai. 1. 15.</note> thou make many prayers, yet will he not heare thee: becauſe thy <note place="margin">Mic. 3. 1</note> hands are full of bloud. Therefore take the aduiſe of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> Firſt be reconciled to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift. But here may ariſe a doubte, whether that God will heare me or no, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I confeſſe my ſelfe to be a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4. 17.</note> and <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>God heareth</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:50"/> 
                  <hi>not ſinners.</hi> How therefore will <note place="margin">He is a ſinner that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeues not the goſpel</note> this ſtand with this petition? very well: for by ſinners in that place, is meant ſuch as be not incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate into Chriſt: and ſuch as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and continue in their ſinne, <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2</note> and ſuch men indeede God will <note place="margin">Rom. 4. 25.</note> not heare. But they that haue put on the righteouſneſſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 26.</note> a true and a liuely faith, them will God heare: and for their ſinnes, was <hi>Chriſt</hi> the reconciliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <note place="margin">Iere. 50. 20.</note> with <hi>Ieremie,</hi> let vs ſay, and beleeue, <hi>That Gods mercie maketh ſinners pure:</hi> for God imputeth not ſinne to his faithfull children, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 32. 2.</p>
               <div type="objection">
                  <head>Obiection.</head>
                  <p>Yea, but how ſaith <hi>S. Iohn: that they which are borne of God, ſinne not,</hi> and, <hi>That hee that committeth</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14467:51"/> 
                     <hi>ſinne is of the deuill,</hi> but euery man ſinneth, and euery one commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſinne?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Anſwere.</head>
                  <p>That is true: But if you well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the words before, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the drift of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> you ſhall plainely ſee, that he meaneth, ſuch as are of the deuil, as perſeuer with willingneſſe in ſinne: euen ſuch, as in whom ſinne raignes in their mortall bodyes. But vnder that power of ſinning, cannot the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God be, becauſe the ſpirit of God, checketh and correcteth, their euill and corrupt affections. <hi>For this victory ouer ſinne, and death, hath Chriſt giuen vs that beleeue. Giuing vs both a will, and a feruent</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. 57.</note> 
                     <hi>deſire, to doe his commaundements. And this is his commandement, that we beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt, and loue one</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14467:51"/> 
                     <hi>another: for he tbat keepeth this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3 23. 24.</note> 
                     <hi>dwelleth in him, and he in him, and hereby know we that he abidetb in vs, euen by the ſpirit which he hath giuen vs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="petition">
               <head>The 6. petition.</head>
               <q>And leade vs not into temptation, but <note place="margin">The word Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is of a verbe that ſignifieth to lift vp, ſhewing that God ſomtimes prooues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> further &amp; higher by degrees, as he did A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> alſo Heb. 11. For firſt he tempted but in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding him to go out of his owne cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly by Sarahs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſt age, and was as dead in regarde of ſtrength of nature: and third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God tempted him in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring vp his onely ſonne Iſaack, of whom it was ſaid, in Iſaack ſhall thy ſeede be called, therefore is Abram called the Father of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</note> deliuer vs from euill.</q>
               <p>IN the former petitions, we beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged pardon for ſinnes paſt, and here we craue Gods grace, to reſiſt ſinnes to come. And ſurely if we looke into our ſelues, how prone we be to fall, we ſhall ſee that we had need to craue of God, that we come not <hi>into temptation,</hi> for that <hi>Satan</hi> intendeth euill towards vs, and ſurely, as <hi>S. Iames</hi> ſaith, <hi>God tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth none to euill,</hi> but man is eyther tempted by his luſtes, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb facs="tcp:14467:52"/> obſerueth, which is a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary temptation, as drunkenneſſe, whoredome, theft, and ſuch like, are voluntarie temptations, or elſe by cruell tyrants, to do that which is againſt religion and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and this is called vnuolun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary temptation, when wee are compelled by force, to do againſt Gods lawes, theſe temptations we are not to deſire. But if any ſuch happen, the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> willeth vs, to account it exceeding ioye, and ſheweth the benefits that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low to them that feare God, and if God tempt or prooue his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, it is to manifeſt their faith to the world, and for example to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: ſo he tempted <hi>Abraham</hi> in offering his ſonne <hi>Iſaack:</hi> alſo the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and <hi>Iob;</hi> yea indeede he tempted all his children ſo, and
<pb facs="tcp:14467:52"/> his onely <hi>Sonne</hi> alſo, that we might not thinke much, nor faint in our temptations. And therefore ſaid <hi>Moſes</hi> to the children of <hi>Iſrael: Yee ſhall not feare, becauſe the Lorde commeth to tempt you, for he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to tempt you, to manifeſt what is in thy heart:</hi> But <hi>Satan</hi> he doth it to an euill end, Yea euer when he tempteth, it is not for conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but ſubuerſion of the party he tempteth, and this is euident through all the <hi>Byble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what ſhall we ſay of thoſe which are dead in ſinne, and haue no feeling of temptation, nor remorſe of conſcience, <hi>(O God deliuer vs from that euill.)</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:14467:53"/>
               <head>The ſecond part of the ſixt petition.</head>
               <q>But deliuer vs from euill.</q>
               <p>THerefore in the next place we pray, that God would <hi>Deliuer vs from euill:</hi> that is ſaith olde and new writers from the <hi>Diuell,</hi> which is indeede the very fountaine of <hi>euill.</hi> Thus we pray not ſimply a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt temptation, but againſt the <hi>euill</hi> of temptation, for we ſee our ſauiour was tempted with three capitall &amp; great temptations, ſuch as fewe of the beſt members do withſtand, and what were they? <hi>Theophilact</hi> telleth thee, they were <hi>auaritia, Gula, etinanis gloria,</hi> coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes, gluttony, and vaine glory. Conſider therefore him that was equall to God, yea thought it no
<pb facs="tcp:14467:53"/> robbery to be ſo: yet for thy ſake he tooke to him the ſhape of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, and euen was buffeted of Satan, that he might the better ſtrengthen thoſe, that are tempted (was not all for thy ſake ô vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <note place="margin">Heb. 2.</note> mankinde;) learne therefore to take vp his yoke, for it is eaſie, and the burden light, <hi>and God is faithfull that will not ſuffer thee to bee tempted aboue that thou art a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> but in all our temptations hee will giue vs a happy iſſue, which God grant vnto vs, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <q>For thine is that kindome, the power and the glory for euer, and euer Amen.</q>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The firſt part</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FOr thine is that kingdom,</hi> this ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth <note place="margin">Reue. 21</note> vs a reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, why we ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:14467:54"/> pray, to God onely, becauſe he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is <hi>King,</hi> and to him we owe this duty, therefore the <hi>Angell</hi> told <hi>Iohn</hi> in the reuelation, that he muſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <note place="margin">Reu. 21.</note> God, for he was but his fellow ſeruant.</p>
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>Obiection.</head>
                     <p>Why, <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>the earth is the Lords, with the fulnes therof, the rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d world and they that dwel therein,</hi> why therfore ſay you <hi>(that Kingdome?)</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwere.</head>
                     <p>Surely God ruleth all <hi>Kingdomes</hi> indeed, &amp; preſerueth bad to, from outward dangers, as you may read in <hi>Dan. ch.</hi> 5. alſo <hi>Eſter ch.</hi> 16. 16. but here we ſpeake of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of grace: by which God rules in the harts of his childre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> after a more peculiar manner, &amp; therefore well may we ſay <hi>(that kingdome,)</hi> for he ſheweth <hi>(Myſteria regni) the miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes of that kingdome to his choſen, but</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14467:54"/> 
                        <hi>he hath not dealt ſo with euery nation.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The ſecond part of the concluſion.</head>
                  <q>The power.</q>
                  <p>THe Lorde our God, is a God of Gods and Lord of Lordes, a great God, mighty and terrible, which accepteth no perſons, nor taketh rewardes, and this is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, why we ought to pray to God, becauſe all power is his, and he onely able to helpe vs. In the firſt place, as he is, our king, he willes our good, &amp; as he is of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, he is able to performe, what him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe pleaſeth.</p>
                  <p>Therfore are we to pray to him, <hi>that he would preſerue vs, &amp; keepe vs,</hi> reade <hi>Num. cha.</hi> 6. 24. But alas, how often hath God manyfeſted his
<pb facs="tcp:14467:55"/> power to euery one of vs, ſo that we may ſay with <hi>Moſes, there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God in heauen nor in earth, that could do like thy workes and like thy power.</hi> How did the Lord manifeſt his power againſt the cruel &amp; blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſpaniards in 1588. yea and how hath he diuerſe and ſundry times ouerthrowne our enimies ſince, hath not this father of ours, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued our gracious Queene moſt miraculouſly? from ſecret conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy and moſt vile treachery? (oh) that we would therefore, praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe, &amp; declare the wonders he doth for vs in this <hi>little Iland.</hi> Haſt thou remembred Gods power, in deliuering thee from <hi>Satan</hi> and ſinne, and for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing thee all thy life: (oh thou redeemed Chriſtian) thou ſubiect of the realme of <hi>England?</hi> ſay thou
<pb facs="tcp:14467:55"/> with <hi>Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 106. 2. <hi>who can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the noble acts of the Lord, or ſhew forth all his power.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The third part of the concluſion.</head>
                  <q>And the glory.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THou art worthy O Lord to receiue glory, honour and power, for thou</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Reue. 4. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>haſt created all things, and for thy willes ſake they are and haue beene created.</hi> And the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>S. Paule ſaith, whatſoeuer we do, it muſt be to Gods glory,</hi> for that is his due, and our duty. Therfore well ſaid a learned writer on this place, <hi>Habes hic etiam cauſam, cur nullae omnino creaturae ſint inuocandae, quia ipſarum non eſt regnum, non habent omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam, nec debetur illis ea gloria.</hi> (that is to ſay) thou haſt here alſo
<pb facs="tcp:14467:56"/> the cauſe why no creatures are to be called vpon at all becauſe (ſaith he) the kingdome is not of them, neither haue they the power, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Illiricus pa. 325.</note> may that glory bee due vnto them. Wherefore, let vs ſay, with the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 108. 5. <hi>my hart is prepared, O God, ſo is my tonge, I will ſing and giue praiſe. (And) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt thy ſelfe O God aboue the heauens: and thy glory aboue all the earth:</hi> and let vs as <hi>(Ieremy</hi> exhorteth) <hi>giue</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 13. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>glory to the Lord our God,</hi> for <hi>he is the king of glory.</hi> Yea, and he onely is <note place="margin">Pſal. 24. 8.</note> to haue glory, <hi>for he will not giue his glory to another.</hi> And for this end are <note place="margin">Iſai. 48. 11.</note> we ſaued, euen <hi>to the praiſe of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his grace, wherewith he hath made vs accepted in his beloued ſon, by whom, we haue redemption through his</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 6. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>bloud, euen the forgiuenes of our ſinnes through his rich grace.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:56"/>
                  <head>The laſt reaſon of the concluſion, why we muſt pray to God.</head>
                  <q>For euer, and euer.</q>
                  <p>THat is, thou muſt not pray ſo, this yeare, &amp; that, for thy Gods name is IEHOVAH, (that is the <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,)</hi> and his time cannot be dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. <note place="margin">Iſai. 50.</note> Therefore is he called the <hi>auncient of dayes,</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>the heauens wax olde, but thou art the ſame for euer:</hi> for his power is not dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, nor his hand ſhortned; Therefore continue thy prayers onely to him, and rob him not of his glory, <hi>doe thy duty betimes and God will rewarde thee in his time</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eccle. 51. 30.</note> (ſaith the Wiſeman) <hi>for the Lord is neare to all them that call vpon him, to all that call vpon him in truth,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14467:57"/> 
                     <hi>he will fulfill the deſires of them that feare him, he will heare their cry, and</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 145 18. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>will ſaue them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Amen.</head>
                     <p>OVr <hi>Chriſt</hi> is <hi>Amen,</hi> the faithfull and true witneſſe, who hath <note place="margin">The ſeale of faith.</note> commaunded vs to begin and end our prayers in faith. And he tolde his Apoſtles, and in them vs, that <hi>whatſoeuer we aske, beleeue we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it, and we ſhall receiue it.</hi> Thus <hi>Amen,</hi> is diuerſly taken in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and many profitable ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, ariſe from the roote in the holy <hi>Hebrew,</hi> I will but onely name ſome of them, leauing them to thy conſideration, and ſo I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thee to God.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, it ſignifieth <hi>trueth,</hi> ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>faith,</hi> thirdly, <hi>ſtedfaſtneſſe,</hi> and <hi>perſeueraunce,</hi> and ſurely moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable
<pb facs="tcp:14467:57"/> leſſons may we learne from theſe.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, to come before God in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> truth, without any hypocriticall ſhew, for he is the God of truth, &amp; hath aſſumed the name of <hi>(Amen)</hi> to himſelfe.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, it teacheth vs <hi>faith,</hi> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to beleeue God in his promiſes for <hi>all the promiſes of God in Chriſt are yea, and Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thirdly, that we muſt not bee <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> vnconſtant in our prayers, for then <note place="margin">Iam. 1.</note> 
                        <hi>S. Iames</hi> telleth vs that <hi>we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Luk. 18. 4.</note> 
                        <hi>nothing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Fourthly, it teacheth vs <hi>perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce,</hi> 
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> to continue in prayer.</p>
                     <p>Fiftly, <hi>Amen</hi> is truely, which is a kind of oath, ſhewing that we muſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> not deliuer vp our prayers coldly, but in vehemency of ſpirit. Alſo <hi>Pagnine</hi> ſaith, it is <hi>Conſtitutum,</hi> a matter throughly determined that
<pb facs="tcp:14467:58"/> ſo our prayers be not a ſacrifice of Fooles. And laſtly in this place it is an earneſt wiſhing, that, that we haue prayed for, may come ſo to paſſe, &amp; ſo is it vſed at the end of all prayers, through the Bible, in this ſence, (ſo be it.) As <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 1. <hi>Nom.</hi> 5. <hi>Ier.</hi> 28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>Here followeth a table, <hi>ſhewing the agreement betweene the</hi> Lords prayer, and the ten comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of Almighty God.</head>
            <div type="to_the_reader">
               <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
               <p>NOw I remember the ſaying of the <hi>Greeke</hi> Father <hi>Theophilact,</hi> that if the Lawe and the Goſpell, were compared together, there is <hi>Chriſt</hi> reuealed in the midſt of both. And ſurely, at the mouth of two or three witneſſes, is euery word eſtabliſhed. Seeing therfore,
<pb facs="tcp:14467:58"/> 
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath taught vs a praier, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the commandements: let vs not thinke the ſonne of God came to giue liberty to ſin, but indeed to deliuer vs from ſinne: yea <hi>Zachary</hi> ſaith in <hi>Luke, though we ſerue him with</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>out feare,</hi> yet it is, <hi>in holineſſe and righteouſneſse, all the dayes of our life.</hi> Therfore ſaid a godly father, vpon <hi>Luk.</hi> 9. where it is ſaid, that <hi>Moſes &amp; Elias</hi> were with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when he praied in the Mount: this ſheweth (ſaith he) that he was no aduerſary, nor contrary, either to the lawe, or Prophets. And that this may more plainly appeare, behold the table, I haue here ſet down, for thy further inſtruction; &amp; chiefly for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction who talke ſo much of Chriſtian libertie, that their life is nothing, but licencialitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now followeth the Table.</head>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:59"/>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalme</hi> 119. <hi>verſe.</hi> 130.</bibl> The entrance into thy words ſheweth light, and giueth vnderſtanding to the ſimple.</q>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Preface of the Lawe.</head>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> Am <hi>IEHOVAH</hi> thy God, which brought thee out of the land of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt,</hi> and out of the houſe of bondage.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">com. </seg>1</label> Thou ſhalt haue none other Gods before my face.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">com. </seg>2</label> Thou ſhalt make thee no grauen im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, neither any ſimilitude of things that are in heauen aboue, neither that are in the earth beneath, nor that are in the waters vnder the earth. Thou ſhalt not howe to them, neither ſerue them: for I am <hi>Iehouah</hi> thy God, a iealous God, viſiting the iniquitie of the fathers vpon the children, vpon the third generation, and vpon the fourth of them that hate me: and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercy vnto thouſands, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that loue me &amp; keepe my commandements.</p>
                  </q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14467:59"/>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The Preface of the Lordes prayer.</head>
                     <q>Our Father which art in heauen.</q>
                     <p>THis preface of the Lords pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er very aptlye agreeth with theſe two firſt commandements: For it teacheth vs that our Father is <hi>Iehouah Elohim,</hi> the bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, as that reuerend Father <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop Babington,</hi> hath well obſerued on this place.</p>
                     <p>The word <hi>Father</hi> teacheth vs, that we are ſonnes of God, &amp; that is, by grace and adoption in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and telleth our conſcience, that he hath deliuered vs from <hi>Egipt,</hi> that is, from the power of <hi>Satan,</hi> and from the curſed <hi>Pope.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the godly in the Reuelation
<pb facs="tcp:14467:60"/> are bid to come out of <hi>Egipt,</hi> of bondmen he hath made vs free, and therefore him we ought to ſerue, and none elſe, yea alone to pray to him, to honor, obay, and ſerue him, and feruently to loue him, as a childe doth his father. Neither ought we to pray to ſaint or picture of any: but to him that is almightie. The worde <hi>Heauen,</hi> ſheweth he onely ought to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and that he alone is holy, to whome belongeth all holy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, neither muſt any be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but he, leaſt the all ſeeing God looke downe from heauen and puniſh vs.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houah <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">com. </seg>3</label> 
                        <hi>thy God in vaine, for</hi> Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah <hi>will not holde him guiltleſſe, that taketh his name in vaine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14467:60"/>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">com. </seg>4</label>
                        <hi>Remember the Sabboth day to keepe it holy. Six dayes ſhalt thou labour and do all thy worke, but the ſeauenth day, is the Sabboth of</hi> Iehouah <hi>thy God, in it thou ſhalt not doe any worke, thou nor thy ſonne, nor thy daughter, thy man ſeruant, nor thy maide, nor thy beaſt, nor thy ſtranger that is within thy gates: for in ſix dayes</hi> Iehouah <hi>made the heauens and the earth, the ſea and all that in them is, and reſted the ſeauenth day: Therefore</hi> Iehouah <hi>bleſſed the Sabboth day, &amp; halowed it.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Halowed be thy name:</hi> anſwereth <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">petitiō. </seg>1</label> fitly to the third commandement.</p>
                     <p>Thy kingdome come. <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">petitiō. </seg>2</label>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thy will be done, as in heauen, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">petitiō. </seg>3</label> ſo alſo in the earth: <hi>agreeth with the fourth commandement.</hi> This king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is in righteouſneſſe, and peace, and ioy, in the holy Ghoſt.
<pb facs="tcp:14467:61"/> The onely meanes to attaine this, is by beleeuing in Chriſt, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith is by hearing the worde preached, therefore hath God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained one day of ſeauen for that purpoſe. For ſurely he that keepeth not the Sabboth day, which was ordained to meditate on Gods workes, and to heare Gods worde preached, can neither be skilfull rightly to know, the vſe of creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and redemption: and if he be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant in this, neither is God his King, nor he anye way fit to doe Gods will, for that is farre more hard to attaine to, then but barelie to know it: &amp; ſurely if any ſhould aske me the cauſe, of ſo much loſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in our conuerſation, and ſo great blindneſſe in this glorious time of the Goſpel, I ſhould ſay, it was the neglect of the Saboth day.
<pb facs="tcp:14467:61"/> Therfore I would deſire all Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, to remember when God bids vs remember, and eſpeciallie the Magiſtrate in his place, that where no conſcience of this dutye is, there may be correction duly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred. For the neglect of this commandement, is the cauſe of breaking all the reſt, and it is the very gate either to knowledge, or an entrance for all the workes of darkenes. (Conſider Chriſtian reader) if the Lordes day were kept of euery one, and ſpent in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding &amp; hearing Gods word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, what delight &amp; knowledge, would it bring thee to, in a very ſhort ſpace. Therefore ſaith God remember to do my will, not thine owne. Neither can we pray thy kingdome come, and let vs do thy will: when in deed Gods will is,
<pb facs="tcp:14467:62"/> we ſhould ſpend the day in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, reading, and meditating, of his meruelous workes, both of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and redemption,</p>
                     <p>Thus we ſee the three petitions <note place="margin">Sab. Mun. on the 5. of Mat.</note> anſwer to the foure firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: both, liuely ſhewing our duty to God, for fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt table, I vnderſtand the whole worſhip of God, namely faith in God, feare of God, confidence &amp; loue of God, euen as it is ſaid, thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God, with all thy hart, with all thy ſoule, and in thy whole endeuour, for loue, truſt, faith, and feare, are in the hart, and in them conſiſteth the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſecond table of the law.</head>
                  <q>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">com. </seg>5</label>
                     <hi>Honor thy father and thy mother that thy daies may be prolonged vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the land</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14467:62"/> 
                     <hi>which</hi> Iehouah <hi>thy God giueth thee.</hi> This ſaith <hi>Paule</hi> was the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement with promiſe.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">com. </seg>6</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt expoundeth this in <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>The ſecond part of the Lords praier.</head>
                     <p>Giue vs this day our daily bread. <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">petitiō. </seg>4</label> This ſheweth that we may lawfully pray for earthly things that are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, but God euer maketh the diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to parents to want, or at leaſtwiſe curſeth the labour of their hands, for the lord hath ſaid, curſed is he that curſeth father or mother. Therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, his light ſhalbe put out in obſcure darkenes. This was the firſt commandement with the promiſe of <hi>Canaan</hi> annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to it, which was the land that had aboundance of earthly riches and was a figure of heauen.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14467:63"/>
                     <p> Forgiue vs our debtes as wee forgiue our debtors, which teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">petitiō. </seg>5</label> vs, that we muſt not onely do no murther, but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhew no crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed looke, nor to vſe a churliſh word, nor conceiue a hatefull ire, againſt our brother. So far ſhould we be from making him our prey, as euer we ſhould reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber him to God in our prayers, this our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our taught expounding this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement in the fift of <hi>Mathew.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adultery.</hi> 
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">com. </seg>7</label>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</hi> 
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">com. </seg>8</label>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe</hi> 
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">com. </seg>9</label> 
                        <hi>againe thy neighbour.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbours</hi> 
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">com. </seg>10</label> 
                        <hi>houſe, neither ſhalt thou couet thy neighbours wife, nor his man ſeruant, nor his maid, nor his oxe, nor his aſſe, neither any thing that is thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14467:63"/>
                     <p> Leade vs not into temptation <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">petiti∣on. </seg>6</label> but deliuer vs from euill. This an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth to the foure laſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, for man is moſt ſubiect to be ouercome by theſe workes of the fleſh, which are adultery, theft, lying and couetouſnes. And ſo the ſum of the ſecond table, is to loue our neighbour as our ſelues.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But deliuer vs from euill,</hi> ſheweth, we are to deſire that God would grant vs his aſſiſtance, to walke in obedience to his holy comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: and this ought euer to be the deſire of all Chriſtians, in their prayers to God, as is ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
                     <p>Thus beloued brethren we ſee that the law is holy and good, alſo that <hi>Chriſt</hi> came not to deſtroy the law, or to giue men liberty to ſin, but to eſtabliſh the ſame, and to
<pb facs="tcp:14467:64"/> fulfill the ſame, which none but he could doe: therefore in a worde, know the vſe and end of the law.</p>
                     <p>The vſe is, that we ſhould ſtriue towardes perfection: and bring <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                        </label> forth fruite, as beſeemeth trees of Gods planting. The end is, that <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">End. </seg>
                        </label> our own infertility, &amp; barenneſſe, ſhould make vs confeſſe, the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the law, the iniquity of our ſelues, and the euerlaſting mercy of God: for wheras by the law we are vnder the curſe, becauſe it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth all vnder ſinne. By the Goſpell, we are made happy through faith in the ſonne of God, for that which the law could not doe, <hi>Chriſt</hi> did, for he turned <hi>the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into wine,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Theophilact)</hi> and that, that was not able to noriſh vs, he hath made good to vs, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for vs. And whereas before,
<pb facs="tcp:14467:64"/> we were bond men vnder the law, that is the curſe: we are now made free men, by him which became a curſe for vs, yea he hath made vs <hi>a choſen generation a royall prieſthood</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Titus. 2. 14.</note> 
                        <hi>a holy nation, a pecultar people:</hi> let vs not now therfore ſinne, that grace <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 9.</note> may abound, God forbid that wee ſhould do ſo, for if we be his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, we haue crucified the fleſh, &amp; with <hi>Paule we muſt be crucified to the world, and the world to vs,</hi> ſo we may be the more able to reſiſt ſathan, when he ſhall tempt vs in our prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or otherwiſe, &amp; let vs that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe <hi>Chriſt,</hi> walke as <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath walked; and aboue all things, let vs not faint in our praiers: for if we be faithful, God is louing &amp; merciful, and he wil giue whatſoeur we haue neede of, for as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>there is no good thing; that he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:14467:65"/> 
                        <hi>from them that feare him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Now the God of peace, that brought againe from the dead the Lord Ieſus,</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Heb. 13 20.</note> 
                        <hi>the great ſhepheard of the ſheepe, through the bloud of the euerlaſting couenant, make vs perfit in all good workes, to do his will: working in vs that which is pleaſant in his ſight through Ieſus Chriſt: to whome be praiſe for euer and euer.</hi> Amen.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14467:65"/>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
